In you. All right. Okay. So, before that, I would like to start with the picture to introduce yourself. My name is Helen Lewis, and I'm the author of the Genius myth. And we also include an introduction. Could you do it again? But, tell me a little bit more about what you do with your. Yeah. I'm Helen Lewis. My day job is a staff writer at the Atlantic magazine and American Magazine. And I'm the author of Difficult Women A History of Feminism. In 11 Fights. And my new book, The Genius Myth. And, So I've read your book, and one of the questions I started feeling was, what did the geniuses of her do to you, to this is this kind of freedom? I think it's funny that people think that I'm doing a kind of hatchet job on the idea of genius, because I try and say really early on, I love this idea of there being wonder in the world of looking at achievements and feeling that they're almost superhuman. You know, that there's I kind of think of it a bit like the way that geniuses work, and the world is a bit like walking with dinosaurs, right? We're just these little tiny, insignificant figures, and it's kind of amazing to have and big personalities, huge achievements around us. But when you have a story that, that, that is that powerful, then that power can be used in kind of bad ways too. And so I took a bit quantify a bit about the dark side of genius. You know, the way that people around the genius get written out of history, the way that perhaps it's not very good for people themselves to be called geniuses? It kind of poisons them. It makes them, you know, when you're only famous for something, some great gift or talent, trying to kind of come into an idea of yourself as a kind of human worthy human person, as a father or mother or child or friend, whatever it might be. I think people can find that quite difficult. People often find immense talent to be a burden, as well as a gift. And so you would say it's not a hatchet book, so you would say it's not a hatchet job. It's not a hatchet job on talent or achievement. What it is, is a deconstruction of this idea.
I'm really fascinating the fact that, you know, we've all probably said the word genius to describe someone who's a genius casually or at least once in the last week. But, you know, what do we what do we actually mean by it? And how is that word changed over time? So I try to, first of all, take a historical look and say, well, the really interesting thing is that to the Greeks and Romans, genius was something that you had. It wasn't something you were. You had a genius that spoke through you. And that's really in the early Christian Europe. A similar version of that would have held two. Right. If you built a great cathedral in the 1200s. It wasn't about your incredible achievement. It was about God working through you. And it's really when you get to the Renaissance and then later to the enlightenment, the 18th century, and the kind of growth of secularism that people become more comfortable with. This idea that there are, you know, little gods, quasi divine beings that walk among us. So you can in some ways say that the genius replaced God in Europe and in America. And if you and the book's title, you say in the book's title, you say genius, the genius myth. Let me rephrase it. Your book's title. You say the genius myth is a dangerous idea. Why is it dangerous? Well, I think what happens often is that it distorts our view of of achievement. And there are particular types of people who are more likely to be called genius. You know, let's not be around the bush. It's more like to be white man. That's not necessarily a problem. Some of my favorite people in the world are white men, but it means that if you are a woman who achieves enormous things, if you are African-American, if you are Jewish, if you are Asian, then actually sometimes you find yourself not getting that label and it's nothing to do with you or your achievement. It's about all kind of cultural ideas about what a hero should be. And I think the thing that really I found most strongly when I was reading this book is this is a book about hero worship. It's a book about who we put on a pedestal and what that does for us. You know what it says about us. You know, if I ask you what your favorite book is or your favorite record, you might be embarrassed if it's something
you might be embarrassed to say. Harry Potter, because you're an adult and you think, no, I should. I should definitely say, you know, it's more an pace that'll make me look more impressive. And there's a similar thing going on with who we know as a genius, right? It says something about us. It says I have exquisite taste or I value this in another human being. And so that relationship between the normal people and the geniuses is also, to me, completely fascinating. That that's, that's I wanted to ask you a bit more about that later, but I was I was wondering first, one of the other questions I had when reading your book was, don't we also need unions to solve the big problems of our time? You know, I. Who else is going to do it? Well, that's the great man theory of history, right? Which is the idea that things move forward essentially because of one incredible individual. And I think there is something to that. I've said to say that's a Victorian idea. It comes from a a brilliant series of essays by Thomas Carlyle on the uses of great men. And the thing that's interesting about going that going back is you assume everybody in the Victorian age was completely on board with the idea of great men. Thomas Carlyle wrote those essays defensively as a defense of hero worship. And there were sociologists at the time, like Herbert Spencer, who immediately said, well, actually, let's talk about social forces. So it wasn't even then. It wasn't an uncomplicated, uncontested idea. But I do think it has some merit. I think that Donald Trump is a world historical figure. I think that Stalin is, you know, the history of Russia in Communist Russia plays out very differently with that, that unique personality of him, whatever it might be in politics. I think that is really true, that, you know, a Napoleon, that the history of France is different, just without that singular figure of Napoleon. But and this is the work of, you know, the trend of most historians, I think, in the 20th century, to be also interested in the interaction between the person and the their time. And what's interesting to me about science now is there's a huge dispute going on about the fact that, you know, Nobel Prizes, for example, in the sciences, are awarded to a maximum of three people. That's really difficult.
If you look at something like the Large Hadron Collider in Switzerland, which is aiming to find out the most fundamental building blocks of the universe. That's a collaboration between scientists from several dozen countries, hundreds of scientists. If they find out something, it's going to be quite arbitrary to say it was this guy. It was this woman. You know, there are so many scientific discoveries to that. Two people came up with at exactly the same time. You know, the telephone famously, the two people registered the patent for that on the same day. So you can get too hung up on the idea that because I think, you know, as humans, we love stories. A person did a thing, and that's how history works. Sometimes two people do the same thing. Some times it takes a whole bunch of people doing the same thing at the same time. The coronavirus vaccine is another really good example. I think you had scientists in China who sequenced the genome of the virus that was incredibly important piece of work. And then you had several labs independently working on different types of vaccine, sometimes sharing some information. And then you had this incredible logistic mechanism of getting that virus off, getting that vaccine to the virus into people's arms. So who who made the Covid vaccine is not, you know, it's very if you if you're going to give one person the prize for that, that's kind of inherently unfair. So that's part of a. I think the people I talked to most was the Turkish. German couple. Right. Right. Yeah. But the people that we had sort of saw as the genius. Yeah. And you know, very often it's about who's got the most compelling story. So there are versions of that. Is it a woman who was overlooked her entire lab career? Is it an immigrant who was discriminated against and, you know, grew up in really tough circumstances? First person and family went to university. Is it a guy? This often happens with scientific geniuses. Is it a guy who has some. Yeah, neurodivergent at the same time. So we're kind of impressed by the fact that somebody who struggles in everyday life has these incredibly brilliant insights and and every example I've given that gives you an idea of
what we're looking for in the genius myth, which is something bittersweet, a sense of struggle. You get something, but something is taken from you. Something is withheld from you. There's a brilliant book about genius. It's called The Price of Greatness, and I think that is key to our understanding of genius. We always feel that greatness has a price. And we just can't stand if people are just happy and a genius, right? It feels wrong. And some of that is the legacy I think of the romantics who came up with this idea of the tortured genius. There's a line. I think it's, Byron, we have the craft are all crazy. You know, the idea that if you wanted to be a really good poet, what you absolutely couldn't be is a nice middle class guy. Just. Oh, I let's, you know, have some lovely flowers. Like I write a poem. Now, you had to be tortured. You had to be an alcoholic. You had to have tuberculosis. You had to be bisexual. You had to have these challenges and tensions in your life that kind of brought forth great art. I think, you know, I think, you can really see this in the difference between Rembrandt and Van Gough. We don't have that kind of mythology about Rembrandt, that he was tortured. He was, you know, an interesting example. And he really loved doing mythological scenes, big, huge canvases. What we love about Rembrandt now is the light in his portraits. So we have a very different idea of what his talent is. But, you know, he made a very solid living doing portraits of middle class, you know, Dutch merchants, right? He didn't have that addiction to the 18th century and 19th century genius myth that you had to be miserable and unhappy or the art didn't really count. Somehow. I was reminded, by the way, with what you said about the great men. There's this, faux focus quote who said, that the finance minister of Germany can only do the finance minister of Germany like these positions, in a sense. And he said, I don't have anything personally against him because all these people are just
colors in the machine. And and so where do you stand on the union? You do think that sometimes there is some form of great man or woman who can? I think sometimes things do come down to, decisions. I think probably more rarely than you think. Something that someone told me recently, which I thought was fascinating, is that we often have this idea of this is the battle that changed the course of the war. This is the pivotal battle. And it's quite that is also quite often a myth, you know, but it's just it appeals to us. The storytelling of it is it is better. But, you know, this is partially an argument between the political left and the political right, which I find fascinating. You know, I got into trouble for saying that genius is a right wing concept because it is. It's about the individual. Right. And if you think about where the, the economic right, of argument has been over the last couple of decades, it's about unleashing entrepreneurs, innovation, you know, letting people not taxing them too much so that they can fulfill their, you know, their destiny and be big figures. And the left has emphasized more equality, giving everybody a fair chance, maybe not making such a big difference between the top and the bottom of society. And genius is quite challenging to that. In its extreme manifestations. It's about saying, some people are so brilliant and so wonderful, they should be allowed to do pretty much whatever they want, and it doesn't matter what effect they have on the people around them. We need that. If you want to have science, if you want to have gravity, if you want to have Guernica, you have to just let these people do what they whatever they want. And they deserve all the yeah, they get and all the credits and all. The I'm inversion. This is playing out in Silicon Valley right now, you know, how should you know? Should, an AI company become the first kind of, you know, multitrillion dollar company? And will that accrue to maybe 5 or 6 people who were its founders? You know, this extreme levels of new Gilded Age
wealth will do, you know, does Elon Musk deserve all that money? Would those companies exist without him? They that's what they think, right? You know, he's been voted by his boards enormous share packages. When Sam Altman was forced out of OpenAI, there was a revolt to bring him back because the feeling was is the company he makes all this value. But you do have. You invested money when you do take into, do you think he deserves or do you think he deserves to be? Do you think he deserves that position that he did that so that it could have been? Do you think it could have been done without. It's very difficult, isn't it, because you always wonder whether or not someone would have succeeded. And it happens to be him. I think he if you read the Walter Isaacson biography of him, Walter Isaacson said, is he has an extreme tolerance for risk, and I think we should give him credit for that. But what that means is he's made a lot of 1 in 1000 bets, and he's the person. He's the 1 in 1000 person for whom those bets have come off. There's probably 999 Elon Musks who are bankrupt, right? Or whose idea never took off or weren't there at the right time. And so I, you know, I think to give him credit for starting these companies and driving those projects forward. Absolutely. I would do that. I would also emphasize the role of luck. And I would also emphasize the role of, you know, you don't build a rocket on your own. A lot of success in those kind of businesses is hiring the right kind of talent. And and having a vision as a leader that makes people want to work for you. One of my favorite biopics is is Oppenheimer and Recent Years, because it's about being a really great manager, and you just don't get that. Normally it's about it's about you're the great scientist. You're the great painter. You're the great writer. No. What about someone who's not that good at physics himself? I mean, better than let's be. Maybe you were amazing in physics, but in the me in physics. But not better than Enrico Fermi. Not better than John von Neumann. He's not the greatest physicist, but he's the only person who can bring those people together.
And I think we underrate those figures because it's harder to tell stories about being a great manager. And if you are, maybe that's actually his talent in organizing this. But we don't like to tell that story about him, and we'd like to paint it more as a genius. Yeah. Has he had. Yeah. Has he had any of the individual ideas or made any of the individual breakthroughs? Well, you could say one thing. He's done it space-x very successfully say I want to use the cheapest possible parts. I want these rockets to be reusable. I just want to change the entire idea of what it means to go to space. I think I give him credit for that. But yeah, you're right. He you know, from everything we know about how he runs his companies, he is both incredibly inspiring to work for, but also manic. And people love it for a bit and then they hate it. You know, and I think that's kind of fascinating is that the kind of relentless work ethic again, it's bittersweet. It's giving you something and taking something people kind of like you. And lots of Silicon Valley companies have the air of a kind of cult, and you join the cult and people get a huge sense of meaning and purpose. They're doing something extraordinary, and it's putting extraordinary demands on them. But sometimes they come out the other side of that experience feeling absolutely battered. I'm not sure. Maybe you can't have one without the other. And I think the. Guy, maybe what makes him more exceptional is the fact that he's not just two weeks old. Right? Building stuff in the world. There's a great exchange between him and the tech investor, Paul Graham, about why maybe Elon Musk might be better at, you know, you might be better at building hardware, which is interesting than software, because actually, the big companies in Silicon Valley for the last decade or so have mostly been software companies, the ones that people are excited about. Whereas, you know, you think of the technical achievement of space X of Tesla and of something like Apple.
You know, Apple is one of the richest companies in the world, but that is based around having an incredibly good supply chain, actually. Has it come out with the kind of groundbreaking products of the Steve Jobs era recently? I arguably know what it is incredibly good is making stuff. And again, that's the kind of genius that gets underrated in comparison to conceptual genius. Yeah. That's interesting. I could I feel the government is milk. I think you might. And there that you don't have to like it's the things they are doing are like space ish is like totally amazing with the yeah machines that they're like, but we can see that there's, there's not someone, there's not a person that you can see that achievements. It's like a team effort. Everybody knows that. I remember people saying at NASA that, you can be a leader. We tell people that I have to put a man on the moon, that kind of stuff. That's, But those are like, harder stories to mythologize, I guess. Yeah. And that's why the word mess is in the title of the book. And because it's not there to say that genius doesn't exist, it's fair to say that it's a story, and it's a story that we tell ourselves, and it's got the qualities of a story. That's the that's maybe because of why is genius. I mean. Because, I mean, in the sense of mythology, like Greek mythology, it's a set of stories about how we understand the world. And it's not reality. It's reality curved into, a method that's palatable that that appeals to us. You know, I think stories go undergo a form of evolution by natural selection. And I write about this in the book they go through, you know, when you hear the story of Picasso, it gets told and retold and retold and it kind of achieves its final perfect form in the in the form that is most satisfying to us. And so, you know, the people get hailed as geniuses. They very often have a kind of caricature of themselves that becomes famous. Anyone who's becomes famous will tell you that, you know, it's quite a bruising experience to find out that there's just
a weird, shaved off version of yourself walking around out there that people have strong opinions on, but that definitely happens to genius. We boil geniuses down to a few kind of key essentials, and that's the that's the mythology. And also we want that because it's easier to have like a person or a face to a certain idea or a certain industry or a certain movement than to have like a whole complex picture of the whole idea of the whole movement. Yeah. And also it becomes a referendum on whether or not you like it or not. If I, you know, you and I can have a very complicated conversation about AI and frontier AI models and whether or not we think that ultimately going to be good for humanity above humanity, but that that conversation is much easier to have if we have it through. Do you like what grok the ex AI model is doing? On on the ex service. Do you like what do you think Sam Altman is a visionary or is he a salesman? Do you think Elon Musk is a genius or a maniac or or both, you know, or charlatan, right? Actually, there's a lot of people who will say to you that, you know, Elon Musk is is a charlatan. So you you become kind of proxies, right? They become aware of having a big, complicated argument boil down to one person essentially. And that's a that's a really useful function that geniuses play in our society. And there wouldn't be any, y, why do people want to talk about these? It's always fun to talk about people who are weird, and unusual and exciting, don't you think? I mean, I write in the book about the fact that, you know, I say I love the paintings of Van Gogh, and I'm just. There's something about looking at them that just provokes this huge emotion to me. I don't know how. I don't know how they exist. You know, that, William Gibson line that any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. I think that's how we feel about geniuses. It's. It's magic, isn't it? Just seeing some the fact that someone was able to do that is extraordinary.
But, you know, the thing that you use, van Gogh is an example. He very successfully married Post-Impressionist painting and the techniques that have come out of Impressionism with his own influences from Japan and Japanese woodblock prints. And that doesn't undermine his talent. And doing those things, it makes the, you know, makes the story to me much more interesting. But he sits at the collision of two artistic traditions. You could say the same thing about Picasso. He is an extremely good conventional artist in his early years. Then he becomes influenced by African masks and, and and by so-called primitive art. And he paints the, you know, Moselle d'Avignon, which is his big Cubist breakthrough. He sits at the kind of collision of two traditions. And that's not to say, you know, I'm not by saying that. I'm not saying Picasso wasn't talented, incredibly talented. I'm just saying it's it's a more interesting to look at him and his influences. But we don't tend to do that. We want we want the breakthrough. And, you know, Would you say that makes, would you say that it makes the picture of the genius more rich and more interesting? I mean, I like it more some people find it, some people find it an attack. I think they find that if you say someone was heavily influenced by someone or, you know, here's this, you know, pre figuration of their work somewhere else, they feel like you're, you're saying that the other that person that they love, you know, wasn't amazing, that they were they were cheap or they were copying. I feel a bit like a little bit someone reading a book. I had this feeling, something that you just said and I wasn't like, I really like the conclusion. But at some, some passages I had the same feeling where I was like, like you were demystifying something that I held wholly, or you know what I mean? Like, yeah, yeah, yeah. Like. This is not entirely, not comfortable. Yeah, maybe. Yeah, I think, but I think that's really interesting.
I don't know about you, but I'm always interested in the things that make me uncomfortable and trying to understand what that is. And I think I also think that I can understand that happening now in the wake of the decade that we've just lived through, where I think there was a lot of giant killing and people were told, I'm sorry, you can't like the movies of Woody Allen anymore. You can't like the Art of Picasso anymore. You know, you can't like, go, go because he spent time in the South Pacific, you know, you hear these people that you like. You're not allowed to like them anymore because they were bad people. And I think there's been a backlash to that, you know, and I and I think it was a it was an unfair thing to ask of people, if you really love whatever it might be, if you really love Annie Hall or Manhattan, you don't have to sign off on thinking that you know, everything that Woody Allen does is amazing. But people kind of don't want that taken away from them. I talked to someone who, had a Michael Jackson song at her wedding. She walked down the aisle to Michael Jackson and about how it felt to her when the allegations of sex abuse came out against him, and the fact that now something that meant so much to her, you know, her wedding, her, you know, one of the best days of her life had this kind of like asterisk next to it that it was kind of contaminated by, you know, by this, this whole discussion. And I can understand why people don't want things that they love taken away from them. You know, there's a big reaction when it turns out that you get these rediscovery, reappraisal of artists or scientists, where we find out that about their feet of clay because people don't want that, you know, I think it happens in science as well as the arts. You know, if you have a hero that you grow up, and, you know, you worship them, it's a bit like the process where I think for teenagers, when they find out that their parents aren't kind of all knowing that, that they can offer me this intense disappointment. But then hopefully you get to the adult stage where you think it's quite hard to be a parent. They did their best and and you forgive them.
And I think that's sort of the adult version of where you need to get to with hero worship, which is I can accept that this person wasn't perfect. That doesn't affect the things that I admire about them, all the things that they produced that I really like. And part of it is that we actually want them to be imperfect, that we need genius to be imperfect. Right. That's interesting. What do you mean by that? Well, they need to be flawed. They need to be tormented. They need to be. That's like what? Why do you like them in the first place? Or maybe not. Why do you like it? But those are the stories that stand out amongst. The stories of struggle. Definitely the stories of genius that stand out most. And I think that's quite moving too, because, you know, I write in the book about Stephen Hawking, who I think is a very good example. You know, the physicist who had ALS and progressive muscular dystrophy, essentially, which put him in a wheelchair and by the end was only able to communicate by blinking his eyes, but was contemplating these incredibly difficult questions of physics. And I think there's something about that that is just mystical to us that you would keep striving and overcoming. But if you read the work of other physicists, they will talk about how that was quite uncomfortable. The kind of celebrity cult around him wasn't necessarily good for his physics work. Probably not. But it made him into a celebrity in the way that his contemporaries, somebody like Roger Penrose, just just wasn't. And there's a related version of that, which is that you want people to be interesting. I mean, that sounds very obvious, but it's been very difficult for, people to reclaim geniuses about whom we don't know a great deal about their biography because there is no mythology. You can't build a sort of story about that. You know, there's just there's just the work. I think, and the controversy is what makes them interesting. And then I think maybe that's what I had when I was reading this or that was like feeling like that was being taken away. I just did it was taking a away and and being able to like, where people just don't.
You should definitely like, wait, I mean, I'm quite a weird person. I'm pro weird people is a concept generally. And I think one of the things that's really beautiful about reading the story of genius is that you find that lots of people who are very different and find it very hard to accommodate themselves to society, nonetheless achieve incredible things. My first book was about feminism. It was called Difficult Women, and it was built around this idea of difficulty, the idea that if you want to change the world, you have to be it kind of at right angles to it. You can't if you're somebody who is, you know, grown up, very comfortable, you're happy with the political situation that you live in. Life is working out really well for you. You don't become a revolutionary. You become a revolutionary because there's something in you that says this isn't right. And you're also the kind of itchy, obsessive, you know, difficult person that is willing to stake their life on, on making this change. And I think that's the other thing. I find very many of those similar types come out in this book. You find somebody like Isaac Newton, you know, just a very fundamentally weird but brilliant man. And and those two things are indivisible. The bit where I think it's dangerous is the bit where we say that people who aren't weird, therefore aren't, you know, aren't geniuses. The idea that if you're well-adjusted so, you know, it's boring. And I think that's that's a kind of fetishization of oddness which doesn't necessarily help the old people themselves, that they have to be special in order to get the kind of pass for just being a bit different. And they have to gradually and they have to gradually start acting more and more. Well, I think celebrity does that. Fame does that to anybody anyway. Yeah. I don't think anybody I don't think any. Does anyone become more normal after they become famous? I can't really think of anyone. Some of them become special because they stay at home. That that in itself is. Yeah. That's being that's that's the most unusual thing to be Paul McCartney. And still to be saying after 60 years is one of the most famous people in the world, is an underrated achievement.
And, would you say area of society and maybe the type of work or the art that the genius has changed over time, maybe you could you take us through the evolution of what we consider genius? Yeah. I mean, I think one of the foundational texts and I write about it in the, in the book is Giorgio Vasari's Lives of the artists. And he had the who I had of great fortune and a great misfortune. His great fortune was to be alive at the time where some incredible artists were working. So, Titian, just after Michelangelo, Leonardo da Vinci. I like this a bit, where I go into things of thinking that the Ninja Turtles. Donatello. Raphael. But, you know, so they had that, you know, in terms of writing about the artist who were working at his time, what a time to be alive. The great tragedies that he wasn't. He was a he was a fine artist. He was a mediocre, not mediocre, was definitely a good artist, but he wasn't Michelangelo. And that must be it must be tough. But he pitched essentially to one of his aristocratic patrons the idea of writing a group biography of the lives of the artists. And he did. And it's where we get the idea, really, of the Renaissance from is the fact that he said, look at all these people at the same time, doing the same thing. And so you can almost trace to him that that idea of the genius, the Renaissance genius. And so, so when you say you would start us, we started out with the Renaissance man. Yeah. A Renaissance man. Oh, yeah. Yeah, I have the American. Yeah. Right. Started out with, with the Renaissance man. And from there I was geniuses. Oh. Yeah. So yeah, I think you get during the Renaissance, the artist, you know, who is, and and the the word renaissance is, is rebirth. So it's about going back to classical principles, and rediscovering that tradition. So that's baked into the idea of genius that you are. You know, this is a movement that is doing something to art.
Then you move on to the I think the next significant shift is the Romantics. And I'm thinking lots of the English poets in Byron Keats, words, sorry, were the, for example, being a, you know, an important text there, the idea of a tortured genius, the poet really is that is the kind of becomes the, I think Shelley calls the poets the unacknowledged legislators of the world. You know, the idea that these people write writing sonnets about, you know, bees or whatever it might be, are actually changing the culture in some way, which just we just don't feel like that now about poetry. We just don't. We have to be tormented. And they have to be tormented because it is about the fact that, again, you you've been given something, but you, you know, there's a cost to it, too. And I don't think you can weirdly tell that story without reference to tuberculosis, which sounds like a very weird thing to say, but it is the romantic disease. Susan Sontag writes about this in illness as a metaphor. She writes about a difference between the way that cancer is seen and, tuberculosis or consumption, as it would have been called, because it's a disease that, you know, you become very pale, you cough up blood, you know, for men, it makes you sort of more feminine in the sense of being weak. These are the kind of archetypes of people hang around it. So there's this really weird line from Byron where he says, you know, I sort of, I wish I had consumption. It would be, wouldn't it be much more romantic if I did, if I was suffering in this, this way? And so, yeah, the idea was that that suffering brought you closer to art, to transcending being human, essentially. And then I think, you know, in the 1900s, maybe you move into this idea more of the mechanical genius. You know, this is the kind of age of industrial, like, hyper industrialization. Somebody like, Thomas Edison, the American inventor becomes incredibly important to America's mythology. So, yeah, sure. Europe had all these the old masters, you know, this was this is the old continent. But here we're America when you we're making stuff,
Edison is called the American Prometheus, you know, after the guy who stole fire from the gods. So this is the idea that, you know, America is just is is forging the future, and it's people, it's inventors who are now the idea of genius. And that mutates into the 20th century dominant form of genius to me, anyway, which is the kind of tech genius which is a human who is has things in common with a computer. You know, they are incredibly good at maths or engineering. They make things that are, again, futuristic. But the price of that might be that maybe they are socially awkward. You know, the nerds essentially, that kind of nerd genius is is our dominant form. And I think that's I think that's still where we are today. I'm kind of fascinated to know what the next archetype will be, but I genuinely don't don't know. Is this, you know, it's it's like, okay. Yeah, yeah, it's the culture was there. It's. I know you just said, you don't. Know, I don't know, I really don't know. But but, maybe we can try to. Okay. Weird. Very good. Good brains. If you see, like, our culture right now, the tech rose, the tech geniuses, they've been, causing a lot of headlines in. They're from the first in our administration. I think the last century. You with the word genius. We think of Einstein now. I think people think of you a of those kinds of, tech, CEOs. Would you what would you hope that our culture shifts in terms of, calling people. To just go outside? So I'm all right. So just silent, like. I think that's. Someone who's right, I said.
Yeah. I'm sorry. And so, You the fire next door? Well, okay. Yeah. Let me pick up on that. Yeah. I think what's interesting about the AI companies is that way that they often talk about their models, they talk about them as geniuses, which is really interesting. You know, one of the things that's not necessarily surprised me, but I think has been very obvious, is that people treat ChatGPT or Claude or whatever the name of the model is as a person. And actually, if you think if you if you read the way that PSA people are anthropic talk about Claude, which is their model, they do talk about it. Is this kind of quasi divine being that they're kind of in the same room with, I think there's a we have an innate tendency to anthropomorphize, to see things as human, even when they're not. And I think that's something that I've definitely seen with with AI models, both from the users and from the people who work with them, who know the most closely. Right? You end up, you start off by giving something a name, and then before long you're worrying about hurting its feelings, which isn't a bad impulse at all. But I you know, I wonder if if we're now treating them, you know, do we treat ChatGPT as a genius? Essentially. Will they be? When the AI models become the next genius AI? It's not that old an idea, really, because they have many of the qualities of a genius, right? Which is that they're sort of superhuman. And we can't really understand how they do what they do, which is two great qualities of, you know, about a great scientific discovery or a brilliant painting. All right. You don't know how anyone you couldn't do it, you don't know how anyone else could have done it. That's also how I feel about, you know, about Claude, essentially. Like what? What is the thinking going on here is the matching. What is it? So I think there's that. The other side of it is I wonder whether or not in a world where computing power is so vast, we move back to human experiences and we value them highly.
You know. Before we go, yeah. But I was thinking when you said the last thing, they're also, they're also actually socially quite. Yeah, yeah. Well, yes. In the opposite way to, to to tech browse. I guess the myth of the tech, bro, is that basically, you know, you can't make eye contact, don't know how to talk to girls. And the problem is a lot of the aim of AI models is that they tend towards being incredibly sycophantic. Like, great idea, well done. You. But yeah, in both cases it took. Like somebody read. Yeah to interact with people, but yeah, you know how to do it. But that's I think both of those are kind of artifacts of the computer age that we, we know so much of our lives now, but our relationship with computers and computing power that either some people pride themselves on thinking like computers or we're interested in computers trying to be human. But, you know, the the kind of the side effects of superabundance are fascinating, which is that what will people pay money for now? They'll pay for experiences, the things that are booming. You know, I want to go on holiday to the place I've seen on Instagram and take a photo of me in front of my, Fuji, you know, and have been there. I want to go to Taylor Swift's concert with 2 million other people, and I'll pay hundreds of pounds to do that. You know, in a, you know, you can listen to dinosaur songs on Spotify for, you know, 0.0001 pence. It's about now what are the things that there's only a limited amount of, you know, art. You know, I thought the theater would have a real trouble bouncing back after Covid. You know, it's it's struggled in some senses, but one of the things it's reliably generated sales is having a, a celebrity casting because there's only, you know, there's only one Cynthia Erivo and you're either in the room with Harry or not, and people will pay an enormous amount of money for that because by definition, humans are limited. Whereas we're now used to this world of the internet and AI, which is just a, you know, there's more stuff than you could ever consume in a lifetime.
Yeah. And think maybe the the idea of the struggle is hard to imagine. Also with a lack of food. Right. I think is a great study about, poetry written by AI in which people actually, when they were blind, tested on it. They really liked AI written poetry, but as soon as they found out it was written by an AI, they downgraded it again and again. It's a defense of what do you want? You want a human connection. You want the fact that there's only so much of something that someone has to give. You want a sense of connecting with a human brain? I think there's a there's a quite a long bit in the book about Hans Eisenach, who wrote a book on genius, had this idea that the genius should either die before 30 or after 80. Really? And and for the under 30s, you know, for your Amy Winehouse, James Dean, River Phoenix, Keats. You know, the idea is that there's something, again, bittersweet, that there's not enough of them. What could they have done? What would the rest of that life look like? You have to live to 80 in order really just to become the kind of father of the nation and influence the next generation. But if you can't do that, then they're the best things to do is to die young. So people will, you know, you were only ever beautiful and perfect and never disappointing and middle aged, essentially. But we'll also will never have enough. And that's part I think that's part of the I story, too. That feeling that everything is impermanent and limited is so emotional to humans. So that will be the other hope that we try to find genius in experiences with people. Again. I yeah, it's a two futures. Are everybody talking to the AI and forming kind of cults to worship them as gods or people go to the park and hang out with their friends like, you know, or go to, you know, a concert hall and listen to music again, that one of those futures seems a lot more utopian than the other one. And is there a type of human genius that could compete with. Yeah, I when I was like. Say, oh,
my life took ages to come and they might be the next five minutes. But I found that foundation where you were okay, a good. My worry. Human genius. Yeah. So, like, where we can find a different kind of genius than the tech world, you know? I mean, I hope so. I think, yeah. I don't know about your relationship with tech. Mine is quite conflicted. I I'm still. I love things that are new and interesting. I'm trying to. I just downloaded cloud code and thought, nope, I don't know what any of this stuff. You know, I never studied computing, but, you know, being curious and, interested in new things I think is is beautiful. At the same time, I, like most of us, wish I spent less time on my phone, less time. Doomscrolling you know, drinking from the firehose, all of these phrases that we have to say that you just it's odd to be disconnected from yourself and so much of life being mediated through a screen. So, you know, I wouldn't mind seeing what the next turn of that wheel is. Yeah, I think, I think, I think my relationship with tech is, yeah, I is ambivalent. I think in the way that lots of people's is. Yeah. I share the ambivalence. But it's, it's. Yeah. And I don't know, in our capitalist society right now, it's really hard to imagine other people than this tech bros becoming, being called geniuses. You find that as well? Yeah. I think it's very sad that. I mean, the book is full of geniuses who all, you know, people who have been hailed as geniuses, who have a really difficult relationship with making money, and quite often, again, the person who ends up being called a genius is the person who's got the best marketing, which is really difficult, I think.
Is it trying to separate out true achievement from somebody who's best at selling themselves as a product is often very hard. So, you know, and artists have had this, you know, this struggle for, for centuries, right. When you in if you're an not in the Renaissance, you had to find a patron, which meant that you had to paint very flattering pictures of a medici or whoever it might be, then you end up with the marketplace and you end up with, you know, people like Andy Warhol or Jeff Koons making art that's specifically about, you know, how much, how reproducible is this? How much money can I make out of this? Damien Hirst art is often very much in dialog with that idea. You know, he made a skull entirely covered with diamonds. That was about the statement of like, what is, you know, what is the most expensive thing I could do to to a dead object, essentially. So I think, you know, these are conversations have been happening for a long, long time. The relationship between achievement and money has always been quite tense. I think it's particularly tense now, as you say, with with what's happening in tech, because there are, you know, the US stock market is so dominated by these big tech companies, you know, and ones that have only existed often for, you know, 20 years, say, you know, we are so kind of there's so much wealth and investment, you know, really just going to a handful of companies in a tiny geographical area in a way that me to me, feels like making an extremely dangerously large bet on a very small number of if kind of horses. I'm not sure that much was going to tech horses. Tech bro horses, horses made of tech brains. But you know what I mean. Like, I would be I would be more relaxed about tech if I felt that there was exciting stuff happening in lots of other ways, but it makes me it makes me sad to think that it's hard now because of things like Spotify, for example, to make a living as a mid-level artist, you know, they're all the superstars, and then it's become harder for everybody else at the lower levels. And I think you probably say the same about the film industry. You know, you can make extremely expensive films or very, very low budget ones,
and the mid-tier is as hollowed out, television, I think. Well, now the streaming boom is over. We might have a similar thing. The same thing happens in science. If you win the Nobel, your lab is funded. Things are great, but actually is research funding for mid-tier scientists. Is that now tougher? You know, people are finding that more difficult to do. And that is that is a story about the way that capitalism has shaped our society, perhaps into ways that are more when it takes all, which is not really healthy. Like I would prefer to have more people doing things that they love and a kind of more rich ecosystem, rather than a couple of really tall trees that you know, whose canopy shades everything else. And maybe also so that, it drains the talents of potential geniuses into one sector. Does it? Yeah. Yeah. People with. Yeah. Tons of people wanted to finance. Yeah, yeah. There's a line from, the book Chaos Monkeys by a guy who used to work for Facebook as something that essentially I've seen the best minds of my generation, you know, training people to click on ads. Right. And that's just that's. Yeah. When you think about what Facebook is as a company, it's an advertising company. You know, it's now trying to pivot to be an AI company because everything, everything is. But that's not and there's nothing wrong with advertising per se, but it's not it doesn't feel as exciting as building a cathedral somehow. But, We spoke to Corey Doctorow. Yeah. You know, he says when the company said they're pivoting, they're being paid. Right. And that's definitely the case with Facebook. They just were like, I don't think there's anything in this AI business. It's fine. And then they just, you know, in the salaries they were trying to poach people on were extraordinary. You know, like the people talking about kind of eight figure salaries. And again, that's a story about kind of monopolization,
you know, would it be in a world in which I write about this in the book, you know, in 110 years, brief Facebook, no matter boom, WhatsApp, Instagram, Oculus, you know, just, just everything being sucked into this, into these giant mega corporations again. Is that the best use of individual people's talents just to be kind of, you know, one cog in a giant machine, I again, I would I'd be more happy if there was if they were, if they were more interesting companies. And you didn't have to just rely on scale. Maybe that's also the way things. Appear. If you understand that Mark Zuckerberg is maybe also an example of someone who's actually proven, scaling up and not really inventing stuff. He's not an inventor. His genius is just based on right companies at the right time and, you know, puts them out there. And then also everybody, starts using them. Yeah. His fundamental insight is, shouldn't I have a website where you can rate how hot people are? And, you know, I'm old enough. I remember that another website that that there was a more overt version of that which was called Hot or not.com, but, you know, but Mark Zuckerberg is an interesting example of the genius myth. I don't write about him so much in the book, but the, the film, Aaron Sorkin's brilliant film Social Network, directed by David Fincher, is really interesting because it makes one very big change to Mark Zuckerberg's life, which is that in real life, he started dating Priscilla Chan, his wife of 20 years, at college. By all accounts, you know, very happy. They've got three kids together. The book makes him a single loser. And that's really interesting to me that they would think that that story is, you know, let's make the creation of this incredibly big website and social network platforming about one guy's quest to, like, make girls like him. And turns out you got a girl to like him. That was not a problem. But it is his. Yeah, he was with the same woman that he's been married to now for a long time
when he was, you know, during all this, you know, this is not a guy who is driven by his, like, resentment at not being able to get laid. But that was a very powerful genius myth of the nerd loser who gets his revenge on the world. And the tagline for that movie is, you know, you can't get to whatever it was a billion friends without making some enemies. So it was all about him being kind of opposed to the world. And if he's just a normal regular guy with who's not massively tortured, it doesn't doesn't really work. Of course, the good thing about Mark Zuckerberg is that with fame, he has had a chance to get more weird, and he's now obsessed with Roman emperors. And this guy named all of his daughters after various Roman emperors. And that which is the kind of thing that I think that's that's what being called a genius does to you. You go, that's cool. My kids after Roman emperors. He started off as a stable genius. Yeah, very stable genius. And, well, I'm, you know, I but I think that I think if you look at biopics, they are really interesting as a way of understanding how genius may get constructed, because the social network both relies on Mark Zuckerberg, the loser, and Mark Zuckerberg versus these two in the Winklevoss twins, Blythe, you know, bastions of privilege. These guys who are just from, you know, who've just a handsome and tall and have got everything going for them. And he's the nerd and the outsider. And for a particular type of guy at the time, that was that was the mythology of tech. It was when you were in high school, there were guys who were the jocks and they got all the girls, and they were really handsome and they played football. And you went to computer club and no one liked you. And but guess what? Now you're incredibly rich and you can have anything you want. And that's. Essentially films. Revenge of the. Nerds, right? But that's that. That is the kind of mythology and that's been a very durable mythology, despite the fact now that there are a lot of extremely rich nerds, being a nerd is a really great thing. Like, any parent would be quite happy for that kid to go to computer club, right?
But that's fine. That's not you know, being the jock is not this sort of socially like pinnacle anymore. And if you were, I'm going to try to ask the question one more time. Just to if you could point to one side of it, maybe it's poets and it's people working with dogs, I don't know, but if you would have like one type of person that could be annoying to the new geniuses instead of tech world, who would you pick? We'll see. You put your poking my at my actual unease with the label of genius here, which is that, you know, I would love to to I would love to find better ways. And I think this is a huge challenge as a writer to talk about the genius of teams or the genius of organizations. And we do have some examples of that. People in tech circles will talk to you endlessly about Bell Labs, run by telecommunications company in the 20th century, just to sort of huge amounts of innovations. They will talk to you about what it's like, how amazing it is to work in a creative team with other people. And, you know my background, I'm a journalist. I have been so happy throughout my career to work in incredible teams, because you can always achieve more together than you can just as one person. You need people to sparkle. Yeah. And I've always throughout my career had editors who have said, this goes on a bit long. Could you make this shorter? I don't understand what you're saying here. You know, that kind of that kind of input is great, but also lots of, creativity happens in pairs. I'm just about to go and talk about John and Paul, the Beatles, you know, two incredible songwriters, but together just, a force much great an who could have been on their own. And we've got a little bit better at telling those stories, but I think instead of us trying to find a new archetype of genius, I'd probably be happier if we could broaden out the ways that we talk about achievement,
to talk about the genius of groups and teams. I mean, and as I'm saying that it sounds phenomenally boring. It's going to be quite the challenge. I'm not sure. Maybe it could be done. I think it's a different way of telling a story that's the problem is we we're so used to the other story. Yeah. Yeah. And so it's a it will take experimentation. But we've been used to the other story since, you know, Norse mythology and, you know, Beowulf and Roman and Greek mythology. So I think that more might just appeal to human brains more. I think we might have to concede that point. Yeah. My kids keep asking me to tell stories about singular heroes doing stuff. Yeah. They don't want to ever hear about Bell Labs. I don't see many children's books among the great teams. Well, yeah. I haven't felt like, the a bit. They have those books. Now there's the only good books, right? Yeah, yeah. Oh, yeah. They're like little people. Big dreams. Yeah. And then they'll. And then you have to perseverance and then, you know, and everybody super enthused all that kind of stuff. But they're always just you feel that there's a meaning. There's like some. Oh that they're teaching you. Yeah. Put into the book. And you somehow, you don't feel that, if you read like, the children's version that you want to see yourself. Yeah. People are. Actually. Oh, this is a this is actually a great leader of this team as well. You it what we also as a team. It's very 18th century. The 18th century had a craze what they called, conduct books, moralizing literature like by Hannah Moore was one of the biggest selling books. And they were essentially kind of instructional texts. And we've given kids a version of that now where we give them books about, you know, about people who've overcome great obstacles in this very heavily didactic way, which is fascinating, because the one thing that children love
more than anything is stories about like, people farting or the road doll stories, which are all about people being naughty, breaking the law, poisoning their grandmother. You know, all these things that are kind of decadent. But, one thing I was fascinated by when I was researching Thomas Edison is the fact that he is now a genius for American children. And I read about the fact that almost no one visits the museum in Menlo Park, his laboratory, and someone I know wrote to me saying, yeah, I went to it. I went to to it, and it was the way to go and it was empty. And so he has become a kind of children's story essentially about. And the way that it's raised with him is that, you know, the 99% perspiration, 1% inspiration, the idea that you just got to work hard. So he, you know, his his genius myth has now moved from American Prometheus to kind of grind set you know, you've just got to get up in the morning and try 100 things, and one of them all will work. The great sadness, actually, you should. Maybe that's like a it will be like a shift from the the genius in our culture. Maybe we're slowly shifting towards. Yeah. You don't you think I. Was the driver. Yeah. Which is probably healthier, right. Because everybody could probably stand to try a little bit harder. But what you can't do is be a savant, right? You're just not born playing the piano at the level that Mozart could when he was five. But you could, you know, you could try it. You could find something that you enjoy doing, you think you're good at and try really hard at it. But that is interesting about though we though we, we fetishize the kind of lightning bulb moment, you know, the strike of inspiration. You will often find many, many people who achieve great things who just grind away that they work really hard. But, and David Gunnarsson has this idea of two different types of innovator or genius, which is the kind of the kind of which he is. He references Picasso and Suzanne
Picasso has this idea. Cubism, right? What if painting. But I'll make it look a bit like blocks where Suzanne works and works away at the same subject. He will have paints the same things. He's just trying to make the best version of this ideal version of a painting that's in his head, and that's you know, and you can see the difference between those two types of, of genius, even in how much their art costs. You know, with with Picasso, people want to buy the Cubist work. They want to buy the art. The idea with Suzanne, the value persists until his much later work because it's about iteration. It's about doing the same thing. It's about perfecting. And I think that that is two fundamentally different ideas about genius. Is it the Big bang or is it the somebody who has a kind of life's work and an a perfect image in their head? They're working towards, Thank you. It's that. If I, I warn you, I. Don't know, but I, part of what I would like to do is also talk about some of these, times. Yeah. Other, other types of will find themselves geniuses. But I think I would like to do that. Stand. Sure. Yeah. You thought they were part of. I really didn't talk talking. That's pretty funny, I did. I think this this overcoat, I think is peak romantic genius, isn't it? The kind of great coat that if you've just kind of leapt off your horse to be part of your grand tour across Europe? It's very.
It's a really, like a German romantic long it is. It really is. Like he's just gone to the kind of ruined gothic castle in which he's about to meet a flighty young woman in a night dress. Hard to imagine. Donald Trump is an 18th century romantic genius. I would say writing poetry. Maybe you could, start going by some of them and then. Okay. Pick one and you can take them off another. Maybe. I thought there's some of these kind of labels, right, that you have. Like you, you say, some people are, Like, millennial boy child. What can I say? Yeah. Okay. What's that? Come behind. So, I'm a big fan of 18th century. Ellen. I'm not sure what he is supposed to have done immediately before this portrait, but, I guess he looks a bit like he's, I don't know, sailed down the Danube or something in an attempt to write his great work about. Yeah, I don't know, mathematics or something like that. That would be very kind of 18th century thing to do. Van Gogh looks, brilliant in this. I think one of things that's fascinating about Van Gogh from portraits is that he's managed to get his. He managed to mythologize his own hair. You always see Van Gogh hair like that. And I think he did a really good job of of making the case that he had great hair. Donald Trump, I struggle to say, is a 19th century romantic genius. I don't think he seems enormously tortured about anything at all. He's a kind of exemplar, I guess. I'm a very 1980s kind of genius, which is just the kind of bullying salesman, that was a very popular kind of 80s archetype. And then. Yeah. Mark Zuckerberg had looks every bit the kind of,
I don't know, whatever the 18th century equivalent is of the millennial boy king supposedly had been born in. I guess if he was born in like 1783, he would have just been around for, the American, the, the aftermath, the American Revolution. He could have been a young American or over to Europe on his grand tour. But, you know, this is what's interesting about this to me is the fact that you can you can see so many of the tropes of, of heroic portraiture and all of these. Right, which is the kind of noble gaze off into the distance is if you're having a particularly big thought, you know, the kind of the tempestuous landscape behind you that reflect your, your personal feelings, which is the pathetic fallacy. And there's there's torment. There's too many. Eyes. And in the landscape. I'm not sure there's torment in, Donald Trump's eyes. He looks like he's going to buy that ship and possibly knock down this Roman forum and, like, turn it into the Trump branded forum. But the rest of them, certainly. Yes, I think so. If you have some of these archetypes, like the tortured rebel, the millennial boy King, you have a bunch of these kind of like archetypes in the book. What if you start on the right when you can pick up the painting if you want, but maybe just say, what kind of genius are we looking at here? So Elon Musk, I would say, is the archetype of the kind of tech bro who is too busy and important to be nice to you. And this is kind of a fascinating thing, I think, which is that the fact that you really essentially the rudeness or the lack of interpersonal skills is rewritten as evidence of greatness. You know, he simply is too busy having big thoughts about rockets to answer. Well, to send anything other than like a poop emoji back to you in emails. Vincent van Gogh, to me, is the archetype of the tortured genius that a lot of that mythology is fair in the sense that he struggled all his life with mental illness. You know, he he killed himself at the age of 37, having sold only a single painting. This painting, I've have to say, this is not a. This is not a Mankoff. Painting.
He would you do made that landscape much meaner and darker. But you know, his sister in law, Jo Van Goff, Bangor. She, lived in this boarding house. I think he was in Utrecht, actually, which was just entirely covered in every single, pretty much every single extant piece of and of art. They had, almond blossom above the fireplace in the, in the baby's bedroom. And she did an enormous service to him by publishing Van Gogh's, letters to his brother Theo, which were all about his struggle, his inability to sell anything, his need for money, his mental health struggles. And that created this incredibly powerful mythology of the struggling artist, which was so important to, you know, how people now interpret the paintings. You would say. He would say she, his sister in law, actually made him, she went to Jeannie. She made him famous. She made him famous. She did all the things that you really need someone to do. You know, if you are a dead genius. Which is? She looked after the archive. She didn't sell off the paintings too quickly. She tried to place them in museums. She created a market for them, and she created this really powerful mythology around them. You know, these were beautiful, but twisted paintings from a beautiful but twisted mind. And ever since, that has just the thing that has affected the way that we read Bank of paintings. You don't look at Van Gogh paintings and think of them often. The emotion you get from them is happiness, and that is that. Is that right, or is that you reading them through his biography? If you look at the irises and, you know, if you didn't know anything about Van Gogh, you might think that's a really happy, colorful painting. And so a temptation is always to read the painting through the tortured genius. Donald Trump is the is I going to say, the political genius, the very stable genius? He certainly thinks he's a genius. I mean, the the case for Donald Trump, not something you hear that much in Europe these days is that he is a singular historical figure.
He has an analysis of what you know is wrong with America and how to make America great again. And he's managed to get people to come along with that, that vision, you know, and I think probably this is going to send some of these things, people gonna laugh at me for saying, I think people will probably see him on the level of importance of a of a Napoleon. That's the that's the of all the people I could compare them to. That's maybe the most flattering, but in the sense that American history is different because he existed in a way that you can't always say about political leaders. And finally, Mark Zuckerberg, the millennial boy king. He's about my age. So, yeah, yeah, I was think. I was sort of feel a bit. Like, how's he doing? How rich is he now? How much better is his life going than mine? Oh, good. Still, still very rich. Is that part of the mythology like the comparison with us mere mortals? I think for people who get very famous and successful, very young, it is because you think, hang on a minute, you're 23 and you've done this. And that becomes another element of the the kind of superhuman nature of what's happening is it's impressive to build a website that is worth $1 billion. It's even more impressive to do it when you're 20, you know, when you just dropped out of Harvard. And for a long time. Yeah. Mark Zuckerberg's youth was kind of, you know, it was the thing that he would wear the Adidas slides, he wore tracksuit bottoms. He didn't wear a suit. You know, there was very much that he remade that Silicon Valley mythology of the kind of the casual ness of it. You know, this is not buttoned up establishment. These guys are young and hip and cool. Of course, you know, lots of them are now in the 40s and 50s. It's quite it's harder. So he's had his reinvention now as a kind of jujitsu bro with his gold chain. And talking about how he doesn't drink caffeine. But again, that isn't that is a very Silicon Valley archetype, right? Doing the martial arts, talking about being masculine again, he's, you know, he he's not immune to fashion, even though you think one of the best things about being a billionaire is that you don't have to follow fashion, but people people still do it.
He was the black T-shirt guy, right? Yeah, exactly. He just had, like, loads and loads of the same outfit. And again, this was part of his genius mythology. He was simply too busy and important to think about wearing different types of clothing. He just wore the same thing every day. And that was one less decision, because he just got to save his brain for making the really big decisions. You have your eye line. Yeah, yeah, I think a few. Sorry. Is there nothing else to say about any of them? I think that's maybe it. Yeah, maybe. Because maybe you can take his picture. Tell me a little bit more. About what? What what a millennial working and feels. What? It's just a nightmare. Maybe you want to put a different label on him. That's also fine. No, no, I think. I think he's I think what Mark Zuckerberg is a millennial boy king because he symbolizes, I think for people, the irresponsibility of Silicon Valley. And that's more forgivable when you're young than when you're in your 40s. So, you know, when you know, the, the, that kind of idea of the Silicon Valley motto of move fast and break things essentially is a bit more forgivable in somebody who is young. Because, you know, that's what that's what young people do. Sorry. I'm staring off into the middle distance where I'm trying to connect my thoughts. It's very hard to think and talk at the same time. It turns out, It turns clear to him. Yeah. I mean, you. Yeah. No, no, no, it just made me. Yeah. Okay. It looks like you are talking to someone there. Okay. Yeah, I think I think Millennial Boy King is the epithet that gets applied to him because he symbolized what was new in the 2000 and young, in the sense that this was a time when everything was changing. People had huge hopes for Facebook and what it might accomplish during that time when, you know it was going to bring down governments and of course, the Arab Spring and all that kind of stuff. So I think his his youth at the time was a really big part of that mythology. And it's maybe why there's been a certain level of discomfort from him as he's got older. He's now in his 40s.
What's the mythology now? What? You know, when you were an aged boy king, when you're just a king, that's not quite as cool anymore? Or somehow, is it? It's not a myth. It's not a myth. It's not all those different types of king. You can become the Henry the Eighth, you know, you can become. The old, fat, bloated. King. But I don't think he's, He's very keen not to do that. I would say, I think can go with maybe a little bit more of a could you take Elon Musk all right. Yeah. Because I think we talked about him also in the interview quite long. So sure. Jordan, with the way. You know, Musk appears in the book. Quite a lot. Because he is somebody that people love to argue about on the internet. And he's also somebody I have these very conflicted feelings about him, too, which is that he has undoubtedly created incredibly interesting companies that, you know, have changed things. I would say Tesla has done an incredible job of making electric cars cool and sexy, rather than a kind of hair shirt. You know, you have to have an electric car because otherwise the seals will be upset. No, you want an electric car? It's cool. And that he did that, with Tesla, with Space-X. You know, NASA was obviously an incredibly important and influential organization in the 20th century. It had subcontractors who were seen widely to be quite. Slow. And expensive. And he said, I wonder if we can be much faster and much cheaper, you know, if we're going to do this thing, maybe let's have reusable rockets. Let's try and make all the parts as simple as they possibly can, as cheap as they possibly can. And then we're much more likely to get to, you know, the Mars or the moon. And let's not take away from the achievement. You know, they have put astronauts living humans into space in rockets built by Elon Musk Company. That is an engineering feat until, you know, until Elon Musk came along, that was a thing that only states could do. And now private company can do that too. So I don't you know. You've seen that one of those. I did I did. I went to Florida and I went to Cape Canaveral.
And I saw everybody heading for the back of the bay. So I had no idea what was going on. And I just so happened that I got there at the same time that they were doing a rocket launch. And it is exactly as awe inspiring and moving as you would expect it to be. You will sit on the lawn and they have the camp dome, which you've seen in a million films already, and then just this tiny little speck of bright orange appears in the blue blue sky. And that is, you know, in that case, that was a cargo payload. But that's still that stuff leaving the Earth. You know, something that if you said that to a human 2000 years ago would have sounded like something that was, you know, only God could have done. And we can now do it. And, you know, I did find that I did find that quite inspiring and moving. What was it, a moment of genius. It it it was a it was certainly a connection with something that felt superhuman, which is pretty good definition of genius. The problem is you go from that. And my second thought after thinking this is so inspiring was why are you on Twitter all day? You know, what are you doing with your life? You can do this. Why are you arguing with people on the internet about conspiracy theories and like replying lol based. To someone's like meme of a frog. And I think that's, you know, that's. Why we love to argue about Elon Musk is there's two sides of him. There's the absolute prick side of him, and there is the side that has done things that are exceptional. And as I say in the case of the Rocket, is absolutely awe inspiring, I think. So the category that he would fall into would be like. Oh, I think it's probably a category all of his own. I mean. The asshole genius or like. Yeah, definitely the brilliant asshole. Definitely. But also like the cooked brain genius, I think as well. That's the other thing. I think he had this incredible brain, but I just wonder if he's just in a way I couldn't live with it, you know? Susie Wiles is the Trump's chief of staff, talked about his his ketamine use. You know, I just wonder whether or not he has a, a brain that runs very hot and therefore has been kind of impossible to to live with, you know, as a child
used to apparently not speak for quite a long time. He was very badly bullied as a child, broke his nose being pushed down the stairs. And also grew up in. Apartheid South. Africa, which I think is, you know, it's very difficult to when you read some of the stuff that he writes now about race and intelligence, for example, you have to remember that he grew up in a society that was institutionally, legally racist. And then the history of race and genius is a really unpleasant and uncomfortable one. And, I'm not surprised that people who are obsessed with genius also get obsessed with race and with with breeding. I mean, the man's got 14 children that we know of. Probably quite happy to have several more. And that's, again, something that afflicts people who get called a genius. They think I must pass on my genius genes, and that doesn't really exist as a concept. You know, I'm sure his kids will be smart, mostly, but there's a concept called reversion to the mean, which means that whatever exceptional range of attributes he had, any kids of his will be much closer back to normal. And again, that. Can be a real that can. Be really upsetting for geniuses. They assume that they'll have like a little brood of kind of tiny prodigies, and they get nice, normal kids. That anyone else will be very happy. With. But to them, it's kind of disappointing because I thought they were going to found a kind of great lineage. You hold this for a second and. It has the exact benefits. Now that really like in the book where you compare the names of his kids with the names, I mean, Bahamas. Marie, I think about Emily. Ben quite a lot. Just normal people, not Roman. Look who Romulus. And, I that's one more question. If you're you're still popular when you read them for the new. Volume. A bunch more just shows without talking.
After the show. Okay, okay. And that one more so. Yeah. Just like in the same scene, I was thinking, I just yesterday I just read somebody saying, like, it was sort of being a little bit you at Ellen online and telling him, why don't you ever post pictures of nice landscapes you've seen or beautiful stuff you've done with your family? I know, I know, he did a very sad post, which was like something like, people tell you that being rich won't make you happy. Like, and it was like, I'm proof of that. And I do think it's sort of essential tragedy in life is to be given everything that you want. And I think that is his tragedy. You know, he obviously had enormously burning ambition to be a world historical figure. And again, it's a kind of genius myth that you well done. Your a world historical figure, but I but quite a lot of people hate you and you can't handle it. You know, it was very sad reading the the emails in the Epstein files about him, where he's trying to go to the island and they go, oh, sorry, no, we won't be there. And, you know, just to be so successful and then but but to still be desperate for people to like you, I think is kind of fascinating. But it is it is a classic genius myth. And what you get is, is talent, power, success. What you don't get is the one thing that you want, which is respect. So there's there's a price of your greatness essentially. And that price is being happy, which is the one of maybe one of the most fundamental genius. Missable. And you're looking forward to his biopic, I hope. I see I feel like Mads Mikkelsen would play a good, a good Elan. But yeah, his biopic would be interesting because you can see there's two versions of it, right? There's the Elan produced and funded version of it, which is about one, you know, child's struggle to overcome their violent upbringing and make it in America. And there's the other version, which is the one talented man driven mad by the internet.
You know, you can have the rise or you can have the fall. So I don't know which version of the biopic will get. Maybe a two piece. Yeah, maybe they like the Beatles. Well, maybe they can make one person. Who likes Elon Musk can. Make one biopic and but that's that, you know. That reflects what I write in the book about the concept of. Biopics is they're mythmaking. So you can make the myth of my triumph over adversity out of the Elon story, or you can make it mine. Decline and fall. How I went mad. The Elon story. And both of those are. True to the same degree. Those are both true about the same person, but which one you pick to tell says an enormous amount about you and how you regard success. Really. So that's you know, that's what the genius myth always is about. It's about what things do you value? Do you value somebody who strove and overcame, or do you value somebody who's a nice human being, an individual? How you go back, you go. Elon, back. On the. Mantelpiece where you deserve. No, if it's okay, just a few shots of you watching and just throwing things. Be discovered.
Explosion victims. And we have no okay, brothers. That's the stable genius, right?
As I say, we're doing a serious. Of. The my millennial boy came there is. When I pedestal and I've been on. Is that actually a safe place to end up a pedestal? Well, it's kind of like that being put in them all, isn't it? You know, someone to look up to, someone to, to admire. But also when someone's up on a pedestal, you can see the for you to for me to say that is the problem. The pedestal. I. Keep thinking if I were going to find to be what instrument for quite like you know on drums went off on bass, let's sing. And obviously otherwise make a fuss. When I make a Tom Hanks at the back. The greatest supergroup we never had. To wonder what John would play. For probably for different genres, we do have an issue. I think if you're going to be genius, you have to you have to really in March to be very drunk, which is not that you, when you're in a band. The two of them were. In a kind of a band for a little bit. Right. Know when Trump. Oh, so you say you know Mark Zuckerberg. Yeah. Well yes. Yes I mean again the story of genius being one of ego. It's not a massive surprise to me that deluge. The Department for Governmental Efficiency. Didn't, didn't work out. Maybe I should put the next to.
Maybe I should just go next. Which are actually, it's the two halves of the American whole. The American dream. And I. Together. Although I think I think they have them made it out, but, Yeah, I think it was very hard for everybody in the white House. To work with. You know, Musk. Jones chief of staff, describes him as a, an old, old doc. But then many geniuses are, which I thought was very kind. Description. Who's not to something your. I they say if we did all of this on this style, we could do the show. So the the movements will show up. You could tell if you had. A favorite, go painting. I, I recently listened to a long podcast about his life. It was actually quite interesting. Yeah, I like the one with, the little cafe, and, I think that's cool. Yeah, that's one of the latest ones I heard that was. Like I said, what I like, I think, and blossom is my favorite. It's very simple. And I like the irises. His flower paintings are wonderful because I managed to not be kind of twee and static and whatever it might be, but, it's one of paintings in the National Gallery I thought, I love so much. I thought The Prince of Action and that he's a tree. I am all right this time. Actually, I did a cross stitch. I did an embroidery version of, sunflowers, which is now my participation. And let me tell you, some of the different colors, the others. You said is here. But don't you think you said this here was like a straight line, right? When you do that? And so I can do this red here. But his brushstrokes are so much a part of. My gosh. I, every time he paints his hair, he always makes it look absolutely amazing with this kind of like, sort of mousse texture and nice and volume and movement.
And I always say you could achieve it like that. Or did you know your you your print like painting technique to your hair? And that's why I just always look so good. Okay. Okay. So. It's just a little okay. Okay. Different. And then we can go to the. Okay. I feel like you should have a bigger, more gold frame for the other ones, right? Because I think at the same time, a frame, especially for Donald Trump is, not a particularly ornate frame. But sometimes. I have something. Which is a name of at my house. My boss. But it's into your available tech, and I don't know, I was first. Introduced him to my boss's. Do you not? My new chandelier. It's just my loves. Interior decoration. What can we say? Yeah, there's a lot of those pictures going on, so I. Yeah, we do a close up with our hands. Just. I don't really look like them. It's like new Victoria's. Yeah, exactly. Yes. It's a very general kind of. But it's also the chin is more so more like a movie star. Yeah. Some subtle surgery. This with all these models that been trained on too many photo models. Yeah. Pretty. Scary what you said about how we might go to the doctor. The Iron. Man. Is this. Yes. There we are. I just read the New Yorker for that.
I got it in the other room. I never really know if it's like, the kind of the mythology and, like the business model. It's part of saying how scared it is, I think. So I think that not happening is going to kill us all. Was essentially, we need to be not to do whatever we want to do, you know, just and I think some of that was definitely part of the kind of musk of war, right? Yeah. I don't know, I could be trusted with this, but, I do think when you talk to people working and then just like that. Yeah, but when I think of it as like, oh, you like Google actually music. Because you basically thought the model was kind of centered. Yeah, I think it's more and more like I think it imitates thinking so. Well, it it's kind of eerie essentially. Yeah. Yeah. You need these moments where it just acts weird and if you like, oh, thank God it's still a computer, right. Those are the words. But would be like, really? The point, like, if you can hide. Yeah. Stuff. Yeah, yeah, you can put it. Oh, sorry. Okay. Go for. Yeah.
Yeah yeah. Okay. Thanks. So. Oh. I, Yeah. Okay. I'm gonna have to go throw. Out! Gabby.
We all love. This. Oh, my. Life. Oh, sorry. The the. Stuff.
That's the different. Myself. Oh. That was like. Yeah. Basically, she brought it back, and that goes into the blueprint. Yeah. Yeah. That works. That's right. You. Remember? Yeah. Time where I. Was like. You talk about. Haha. Yes. I brought you here to see Horatio Nelson, England's great naval hero. And Nelson's Column is put up immediately after he wins the Battle of Trafalgar and is killed during the Battle of Trafalgar. And I think it's such a great place to be to talk about genius, because statues
are one of the ways that we argue about who deserves to be celebrated. That's right. Yeah, we do it. Yeah, yeah. Oh yeah. Because I have no. Yeah, yeah. So, Yeah, we're talking about, This is a pretty huge pedestal. And that is Horatio Nelson, England's great naval hero. Nelson's column was built to celebrate his victory over the French and the Spanish at the Battle of Trafalgar, at which he also was killed. And the last couple of years, we've had all these arguments about statues and the kind of part of the argument about genius is to because it's about who do we celebrate? And do we still celebrate the same people that we did 100 years ago, 200 years ago? So the ratio, Nelson, as far as I understand, has not been canceled. But you will walk around London and see statues of people who at the time were hailed as geniuses, who we now feel are a bit more uncomfortable. There's a very big debate, for example, about Britain's great war hero Winston Churchill, but who was also involved in the Bengal famine. Actually, one of the things that's great about being here is just around the corner behind me. You can't see it. There's one of the very few statues of a named woman, Edith Campbell, nurse during the First World War. And actually, one of the things you can see, we talk about genius being very male. Statues are very male. Two, they represent a very male type of achievement. And, you know, that's why the the subject to many of the same debates that we have over geniuses. Would say maybe he got killed. It definitely helps because he gave everything for for his country, you know, and, and I also think it helps to have I mean, there's something very funny almost, about how very big that column is. It's I think we would say extra. I don't think they would have described it that way at me at the time, but it's very much like I have got the biggest column. You know, there's plenty of statues around London, but there's only one Nelson's Column.
I know that is about the fact that he was to the people who made that the greatest military hero that we had at the time. What was it about us. That we as a species know what this is about is that we like to. Talk about something like. I think we love to put people on pedestals because it's a way of saying what we value that statue is, and that column is to commemorate somebody who gave their life for an idea of Britain, an idea of the nation. Great time. So many things. Like. It's on the mile in the middle of the. Yeah. I don't want to get run over that. I mean. I'm just asking for someone. Yeah. What is it about for me personally, I think we love to hero worship. I think that's a pretty natural human impulse. And also to find out whether or not other people value the same things that we do. You know, we don't want to just listen to record alone. We want to go to a concert with loads of other people who like that record, too. If we hail someone's a genius. We want to know that other people value them to the same extent we do. In the case of a military hero, you know, that's about saying, here's an idea of us as a nation and this is what we all believe. And, you know, Nelson is a British hero. But what's interesting about being here is you can also see the backlash and follow the square. So therefore lines around the base of that plinth, there's also four separate plinths. And now for many decades that has been the idea of the fourth plinth. And that has been about celebrating different ideals for a long time. One of the statues on it, very famously, was Marc Quinn's sculpture Alison Lapper Pregnant. And she had limb shortening from, for the demise.
And she was pregnant, so she didn't look like people in classical statues do. And having that as a public artwork was about saying we value something slightly differently. You know, we don't value people who are quote unquote perfect. We value somebody who has made something about life through struggle. And they have been more community based, always about celebrating minorities and marginalized people. And then you can see the push and pull of the genius myth. Is it about celebrating the great man on the pedestal, or do we need sometimes to celebrate more ordinary lives, more ordinary people? Sorry. And yet you can't put a team on a pedestal. That's probably where the genius of teams is has gone wrong all these years. Okay, thank you. Yes. You mentioned the. I'm not sure all. I'm going to take you to see Edith Cavell, who was a World War One nurse. And there's something that's really interesting about the statue is that she was one of the very, very few named women to get a statue. That happens for all the reasons that you'd expect. You know, the great historians, the politicians, the prime ministers throughout history have been men. And you get sometimes these female statues that are about the personification in victory. But until very recently, it has been extremely, extremely rare to have a woman who is celebrated enough in her own right to get a statue. Yes, it's like, well. That's been around for quite a while, but we do now have a new one, which is of Millicent Garrett Fawcett in Parliament Square. She was a suffragist.
She campaigned for women to get the vote. And what is important about that statue is that it is the first female statue in Parliament Square, and it's someone who campaigned for women to get the vote. So it's about saying women belong in Parliament, women belong in Parliament Square. The genius of someone like Millicent Garrett Fawcett, who organized a kind of army of suffragists that deserves to be celebrated. For. It. So I'm taking you to see Edith Cavell, who was one of the very few named women to have a statue in London or actually anywhere in Britain. And I always make sure that I come and look at the statue whenever I walk past. Phoebe. That's right. The night. So I'm taking you to see Edith Cavell, who was a nurse during the First World War. And she's remarkable because this is one of the very few statues we have in London or anywhere in Britain, of a named woman who's not Queen Victoria. There's a few Queen Victoria's. And I think this is interesting about what Edith Cowan was being celebrated for. She was a nurse who treated both Allied soldiers, German soldiers, equally and was executed by firing squad. And when she died, she said, I bear no ill will against anyone else. So she's being celebrated for a kind of very feminine set of qualities, which is a bit different to what Nelson is being celebrated for. The kind of more male genius, the military genius. You know, you know. That. Somehow it's also maybe. I get it like.
We do have these little geniuses, and now we're sort of starting to order geniuses. Yeah. We can say, like. Who is the, But she's at all. It's very tempting to say, but actually, we can save ourselves a lot of grief by not putting up statues. But that's like saying we shouldn't have geniuses. The whole point of putting up a statue is to have an argument about what you value and what you as a country and a society value. And that's exactly the same reason that we appoint someone to be a genius. Okay. What do we value in Edith Cavell? We value sacrifice and duty and the type of patriotism that she said. It's not enough to have patriotism. You also have to kind of have love for everybody. That's a specific set of ideals that are being celebrated here. And that's the same thing that happens when we pick a genius. When we anoint strings, it may sound, we may know a Taylor Swift, you know, what does Taylor Swift represent to us? Well, talent, but also hard work, but also, you know, turning up and putting on a show every night of the week, whatever it might be. It's how we talk about. Our values and the. She loves us. Yeah. So Edith Havel was a sorry. So Edith Cavell was a nurse during the First World War who treated both sides equally. But she was executed by a German firing squad and this was an outrage at the time. You know, they said, well, what has she done? She's not an enemy combatant. And so there's a statue to her, which is very rare for a woman, but because she represents something. And that's the argument that I make all the way through. The genius myth is that geniuses represent something. They get statues made to them, they get museums dedicated to them because they represent something.
We need to make more of these people geniuses. Once we get that. I think there is a lively debate now about whether or not she was secretly a spy. So even the most, you know, apparently bland celebration of, you know, sort of nursing duty might have a little edge to it underneath. And I don't think you can get away from those arguments. You know, what I value is what I value is always going to be different to what you value. And we have to find a way in a society of kind of finding the middle ground between those things. But you might not want that statue. I might want this one. You might not want another one. I might want it. And that's exactly the same with, you know, who you hero. Worship is very different to who I hero worship. But yeah, more, more weird statues. That's what I would like. One of the things that's been great about the fourth plinth in Trafalgar Square is just expanding the range of things that count as public art, and I think that's that's wonderful. Right, right. Okay, there's one other thing I can say about this. Be. For the one. Of the other things that's interesting about having public art of somebody who talked about patriotism not being enough and died in the First World War is that you quite often see anti-war protesters around here, or people protesting around war crimes. And statues are a kind of focal point for those kind of discussions in exactly the same way that it mattered. But Albert Einstein was very worried about the nuclear bomb, because there was a person that you could point to, a focus, a rallying point around which you could have this big argument. He's a genius. He's worried about this. That makes it okay for us to worry about it, too. Edith Cavell shows in the dark side of of War, not the kind of glory and the patriotism of it. So she becomes a focal point for people to talk about things that they want to talk about. Let's stop here. Okay. It's on my way to work.
So I kind of say hello to her quite often in the morning when I go past, I don't I don't say hello to Nelson. I don't know that much about Nelson. And that's one of the interesting things too, is that Nelson is a figure of national mythology for British people, for English people, but actually not in the culture in a particularly strong way. It will take somebody deciding that they love Nelson, they want to make the Nelson biopic or whatever it is to bring him back again. But yeah, I do, I do. Stop and say hello to Edith. Travel in the morning. But. He has a bit of a tormented forward. Kind of coping. I think that's just the extremely high neckline. Yeah, but it's interesting that she's she's posed in a very heroic way. It's a very kind of it's a very, like, manly striding pose. And again, that's why statues are part of the kind of iconography of genius it's about in the same way the portraits are, it's about presenting somebody as being grandeur. Why statues big? Why are people so often on horseback? It's about saying that they are superhuman. They're different to us somehow. They're not like ordinary people. The geniuses. Thanks for the rain. Yeah. That. Is is it
the offices in. Thank local radio. The barn. The kind of, more popular of the people. But sometimes you have cities. We have. Parts where it's just like, oh, that's. Great, right? Yeah. That's. Just. Yeah. Going. Going to start to. Send that to them. And the other one for. Okay. That's fine for. Yourself. Okay. You're going you're they, you're. I it.
Looks like a whole. The, like the ground floor. Your heart. Will be the on the kind of the home again. And there will be. More resources. There. When you're ready for. Really? Next, next.
Month from there, we will follow you all the way around. We. Will ask you a question there. Or maybe here for a. Yeah, yeah. So this is. About this as great man as it gets, right? Was Winston Churchill a genius? If you want to start a fight in a pub in Britain, that's a pretty good question to throw out there. To some people, Winston Churchill is unquestionably a genius. If you look at how he came to power, the Nazis were on the march. Britain was pursuing a policy of appeasement, and he was the person who came in and said, there's you know, Britain fights on Britain and Britain alone will stand against the Nazis, and therefore he's a national hero. But there are some checkered bits in the back story, too.
He will too. Lots of people forever be associated with the Bengal famine, which left millions dead in his career as a kind of colonial overseer. And so people have these big debates, which is the real Winston Churchill. Is he the genius who galvanized this nation to stand against Nazis, or is he the kind of feckless colonialist of the Bengal famine? Maybe he's and he's both. I mean, this is why we can always argue about geniuses, because he's both you know, I think there's a huge amount to be proud of. Winston Churchill. But we don't need to airbrush out the bad bits of the biography two. In fact, they're more interesting because they're what makes him human, right? He's not just the guy on the pedestal. He was a real human being. And, you know, the other thing that's become part of his mythology in recent years is the black dog, his depression. He was somebody who suffered from really poor mental health at certain times. But there's something noble about the way that he nonetheless galvanized himself and the country that really difficult and dark moments. Because also say something about us that we need people like this to have these kind of the trenches of torment where we used to just be like, oh, he's a war hero, great guy. I think that's the thing I think people were more comfortable at just having a straightforward mythology of the great man. Now we want to hear about how did the great man struggle and what did the great man find difficult to do? And we want to see the real person underneath. You know, if you watch I watched The Darkest Hour, which is a Churchill biopic, and there's scenes of him in the bath and this would have been, you know, in 1950, that would have been a really shocking thing to, to say and talk about. And now we kind of want that. We want the human side of the genius. Would you say he's like an example of the queen of this great man theory of history, but also a great man? I think he's an obvious example of a great man of history. That decision to replace Neville Chamberlain with Winston Churchill is a pivotal moment in the Second World War,
and that is exactly what Great man theory is all about. It's about one person being vitally important to the course of events. It's a part of who you stand on. Why do I stand on Winston Churchill? Yes. Oh, no. Look, I think that maybe. The Winston Churchill genius. Or Winston Churchill, a political genius, undoubtedly, because what he did was taking a country that needed to believe in itself to do something which was undoubtedly morally correct, which was stand against the Nazis. And he did that. He pulled everybody together. And to me, that is still one of the most extraordinary things in Britain's history, and something I think that Britain can still, 80 years on, be incredibly proud about. But but I to say that I don't need to airbrush out the earlier Winston Churchill and I think that's the thing. But what do you think about people like that? You should have your you. You shouldn't, like, pry too much into these lines or. There it's a left wing, right wing argument essentially, which is there's a feeling that if you debunk Winston Churchill, that's taking something away from Britain, that's taking away a particular story of Britain's history, saying maybe Britain should be a bit more ashamed of its past versus people who say Britain, we should be proud of our history. And this is an argument that happens across Europe, it happens in America, it happens in Britain. And genius is a part of that story. Can you be proud of a genius? Can you be proud of an English genius and what they say about England? And that's wrapped up in questions about patriotism. I guess is right. It is really the change. Yeah. That's right. Today I get this, you have this right with the French, right? Just about all the stuff during the game. Powers like this guy.
Right? With regret, for instance, that you should feel about this, right? Community. Yeah. And we're all ready for the fight. He basically feels like this, Let's face it this way. Some get the feeling. You know, I think you. I think you have to be an adult about this stuff. I think that the fact that Winston Churchill. Even more, I think after you said with these rifles and. I'm going zero, but. Okay, let's go through what can we just do?