In you.
All right.
Okay.
So, before that,
I would like to start with the picture
to introduce yourself.
My name is Helen Lewis,
and I'm the author of the Genius myth.
And we also include an introduction.
Could you do it again?
But, tell me a little bit more
about what you do with your.
Yeah.
I'm Helen Lewis.
My day job is a staff writer at the
Atlantic magazine and American Magazine.
And I'm the author of Difficult Women
A History of Feminism.
In 11 Fights.
And my new book, The Genius Myth. And,
So I've read your book,
and one of the questions
I started feeling was,
what did the geniuses of her do to you, to
this is this kind of freedom?
I think it's funny that people think
that I'm doing a kind of hatchet job
on the idea of genius,
because I try and say really early on,
I love this idea
of there being wonder in the world
of looking at achievements and feeling
that they're almost superhuman.
You know, that there's
I kind of think of it
a bit like the way that geniuses work,
and the world is a bit like walking
with dinosaurs, right?
We're just these little tiny,
insignificant figures,
and it's kind of amazing
to have and big personalities,
huge achievements around us.
But when you have a story
that, that, that is that powerful,
then that power can be used
in kind of bad ways too.
And so I took a bit quantify
a bit about the dark side of genius.
You know, the way that people around
the genius get written out of history,
the way that perhaps it's not very good
for people themselves to be called
geniuses?
It kind of poisons them.
It makes them,
you know, when you're only famous
for something, some great gift or talent,
trying to kind of come
into an idea of yourself
as a kind of human worthy human person,
as a father or mother or child or friend,
whatever it might be.
I think people can find that
quite difficult.
People often find immense
talent to be a burden, as well as a gift.
And so you would say
it's not a hatchet book,
so you would say it's not a hatchet job.
It's not a hatchet
job on talent or achievement.
What it is,
is a deconstruction of this idea.
I'm really fascinating the fact
that, you know, we've all probably said
the word genius to describe
someone who's a genius casually
or at least once in the last week.
But, you know, what do we
what do we actually mean by it?
And how is that word changed over time?
So I try to, first of all,
take a historical look and say, well,
the really interesting thing
is that to the Greeks and Romans, genius
was something that you had.
It wasn't something you were.
You had a genius that spoke through you.
And that's really in the early Christian
Europe.
A similar version of
that would have held two. Right.
If you built a great cathedral
in the 1200s.
It wasn't
about your incredible achievement.
It was about God working through you.
And it's really
when you get to the Renaissance
and then later to the enlightenment,
the 18th century,
and the kind of growth of secularism
that people become more comfortable with.
This idea that there are,
you know, little gods, quasi
divine beings that walk among us.
So you can in some ways say that the genius replaced God in Europe and in America.
And if you
and the book's title,
you say in the book's title, you say
genius, the genius myth.
Let me rephrase it.
Your book's title.
You say the genius
myth is a dangerous idea.
Why is it dangerous?
Well, I think what happens often is that
it distorts our view of of achievement.
And there are particular types of people
who are more likely to be called genius.
You know, let's not be around
the bush. It's more like to be white man.
That's not necessarily a problem.
Some of my favorite people in the world
are white men,
but it means that if you are a woman
who achieves enormous things,
if you are African-American,
if you are Jewish, if you are Asian,
then actually sometimes you find yourself
not getting that label
and it's nothing to do with you
or your achievement.
It's about all kind of cultural ideas
about what a hero should be.
And I think the thing that really
I found most strongly
when I was reading this book is
this is a book about hero worship.
It's a book about who we put on a pedestal
and what that does for us.
You know what it says about us.
You know,
if I ask you what your favorite book is
or your favorite record,
you might be embarrassed if it's something
you might be embarrassed to say.
Harry Potter, because you're an adult
and you think, no, I should.
I should definitely say, you know, it's
more an pace
that'll make me look more impressive.
And there's a similar thing going on
with who we know as a genius, right?
It says something about us.
It says I have exquisite taste
or I value this in another human being.
And so that relationship
between the normal people
and the geniuses is also,
to me, completely fascinating.
That that's, that's I wanted
to ask you a bit more about that later,
but I was I was wondering first,
one of the other questions
I had when reading your book was,
don't we also need unions
to solve the big problems of our time?
You know, I.
Who else is going to do it?
Well, that's the great man
theory of history, right?
Which is the idea
that things move forward essentially
because of one incredible individual.
And I think there is something to that.
I've said to say that's a Victorian idea.
It comes from a
a brilliant series of essays by Thomas
Carlyle on the uses of great men.
And the thing that's interesting
about going that going back
is you assume everybody in the Victorian
age was completely on board
with the idea of great men.
Thomas Carlyle wrote those essays
defensively as a defense of hero worship.
And there were sociologists at the time,
like Herbert Spencer,
who immediately said, well, actually,
let's talk about social forces.
So it wasn't even then.
It wasn't
an uncomplicated, uncontested idea.
But I do think it has some merit.
I think that Donald Trump is a world
historical figure.
I think that Stalin is, you know,
the history of Russia in Communist
Russia plays out very differently
with that, that unique personality of him,
whatever it might be in politics.
I think that is really true, that,
you know, a Napoleon,
that the history of France is different,
just without that singular
figure of Napoleon.
But and this is the work of,
you know, the trend of most historians,
I think, in the 20th century,
to be also interested in the interaction
between the person and the their time.
And what's interesting to me about science
now is there's a huge dispute going on
about the fact that,
you know, Nobel Prizes,
for example, in the sciences,
are awarded to a maximum of three people.
That's really difficult.
If you look at something like the Large
Hadron Collider in Switzerland,
which is aiming to find out
the most fundamental
building blocks of the universe.
That's a collaboration between scientists
from several dozen
countries, hundreds of scientists.
If they find out something, it's
going to be quite arbitrary to say
it was this guy. It was this woman.
You know, there are so many scientific
discoveries to that.
Two people came up
with at exactly the same time.
You know, the telephone famously,
the two people registered the patent
for that on the same day.
So you can get too hung up on the idea
that because I think, you know, as humans,
we love stories.
A person did a thing,
and that's how history works.
Sometimes two people do the same thing.
Some times it takes a whole
bunch of people doing the same thing
at the same time.
The coronavirus vaccine
is another really good example.
I think you had scientists in China
who sequenced the genome of the virus
that was incredibly
important piece of work.
And then you had several labs
independently
working on different types of vaccine,
sometimes sharing some information.
And then you had this incredible
logistic mechanism
of getting that virus off, getting that
vaccine to the virus into people's arms.
So who who made the Covid vaccine is not,
you know, it's very
if you if you're going to give one person
the prize for that,
that's kind of inherently unfair.
So that's part of a.
I think the people I talked to
most was the Turkish.
German couple. Right. Right. Yeah.
But the people that we had sort of saw
as the genius.
Yeah.
And you know, very often it's about
who's got the most compelling story.
So there are versions of that.
Is it a woman who was overlooked
her entire lab career?
Is it an immigrant
who was discriminated against and,
you know, grew up
in really tough circumstances?
First person
and family went to university.
Is it a guy?
This often happens
with scientific geniuses.
Is it a guy who has some.
Yeah, neurodivergent at the same time.
So we're kind of impressed by the fact
that somebody who struggles in
everyday life
has these incredibly brilliant insights
and and every example
I've given that gives you an idea of
what we're looking for in the genius myth,
which is something bittersweet,
a sense of struggle.
You get something,
but something is taken from you.
Something is withheld from you.
There's a brilliant book about genius.
It's called The Price of Greatness,
and I think that is key
to our understanding of genius.
We always feel that greatness has a price.
And we just can't stand if people are just
happy and a genius, right?
It feels wrong.
And some of that is the legacy
I think of the romantics
who came up with this idea
of the tortured genius.
There's a line.
I think it's, Byron, we have
the craft are all crazy.
You know, the idea that
if you wanted to be a really good poet,
what you absolutely
couldn't be is a nice middle class guy.
Just. Oh, I let's,
you know, have some lovely flowers.
Like I write a poem.
Now, you had to be tortured.
You had to be an alcoholic.
You had to have tuberculosis.
You had to be bisexual.
You had to have these challenges
and tensions in your life
that kind of brought forth great art.
I think, you know, I think,
you can really see this in the difference
between Rembrandt and Van Gough.
We don't have
that kind of mythology about Rembrandt,
that he was tortured.
He was, you know, an interesting example.
And he really loved doing
mythological scenes, big, huge canvases.
What we love about Rembrandt
now is the light in his portraits.
So we have a very different idea
of what his talent is.
But, you know, he made a very solid living
doing portraits
of middle class,
you know, Dutch merchants, right?
He didn't have that addiction to the 18th
century and 19th century genius myth
that you had to be miserable and unhappy
or the art didn't really count.
Somehow.
I was reminded, by the way,
with what you said about the great men.
There's this,
faux focus quote who said,
that the finance minister of Germany
can only do
the finance minister of Germany
like these positions, in a sense.
And he said, I don't have
anything personally against him
because all these people are just
colors in the machine.
And and so
where do you stand on the union?
You do think that sometimes there is
some form of great man or woman who can?
I think sometimes things do come down
to, decisions.
I think probably more rarely than you
think.
Something that someone told me recently,
which I thought was fascinating,
is that we often
have this idea of this is the battle
that changed the course of the war.
This is the pivotal battle.
And it's quite
that is also quite often a myth,
you know, but it's just it appeals to us.
The storytelling of it is it is better.
But, you know,
this is partially an argument
between the political left and the
political right, which I find fascinating.
You know, I got into trouble for saying
that genius is a right wing concept
because it is.
It's about the individual. Right.
And if you think about where the,
the economic right,
of argument has been over the last couple
of decades, it's about
unleashing entrepreneurs, innovation,
you know, letting people
not taxing them too much
so that they can fulfill their,
you know, their destiny
and be big figures.
And the left has emphasized more equality,
giving everybody a fair chance,
maybe not making such a big difference
between the top and the bottom of society.
And genius is quite challenging to that.
In its extreme manifestations.
It's about saying,
some people are so brilliant
and so wonderful,
they should be allowed to do pretty much
whatever they want, and it doesn't matter
what effect
they have on the people around them.
We need that.
If you want to have science,
if you want to have gravity,
if you want to have Guernica,
you have to just let these people do
what they whatever they want.
And they deserve all the yeah, they get
and all the credits and all.
The I'm inversion.
This is playing out in Silicon Valley
right now, you know, how should you know?
Should,
an AI company become the first kind of,
you know, multitrillion dollar company?
And will that accrue to maybe 5
or 6 people who were its founders?
You know, this
extreme levels of new Gilded Age
wealth will do, you know,
does Elon Musk deserve all that money?
Would those companies exist without him?
They that's what they think, right?
You know, he's been voted by his boards
enormous share packages.
When Sam Altman was forced out of OpenAI,
there was a revolt to bring him back
because the feeling was is the company
he makes all this value.
But you do have.
You invested money when you do take into,
do you think
he deserves
or do you think he deserves to be?
Do you think he deserves that position
that he did that
so that it could have been?
Do you think it could have been done
without.
It's very difficult, isn't it,
because you always wonder whether or not
someone would have succeeded.
And it happens to be him.
I think he if you read the Walter Isaacson
biography of him, Walter Isaacson
said, is
he has an extreme tolerance for risk,
and I think we should give him
credit for that.
But what that means is he's made a lot of
1 in 1000 bets, and he's the person.
He's the 1 in 1000 person for whom
those bets have come off.
There's probably 999 Elon Musks
who are bankrupt, right?
Or whose idea never took off
or weren't there at the right time.
And so I, you know,
I think to give him credit
for starting these companies
and driving those projects forward.
Absolutely. I would do that.
I would also emphasize the role of luck.
And I would also emphasize the role
of, you know,
you don't build a rocket on your own.
A lot of
success in those kind of businesses
is hiring the right kind of talent.
And and having a vision as a leader
that makes people want to work for you.
One of my favorite biopics
is is Oppenheimer
and Recent Years, because it's about being
a really great manager,
and you just don't get that.
Normally it's about it's about
you're the great scientist.
You're the great painter.
You're the great writer.
No. What about someone
who's not that good at physics himself?
I mean, better than let's be.
Maybe you were amazing in physics,
but in the me in physics.
But not better than Enrico Fermi.
Not better than John von Neumann.
He's not the greatest physicist,
but he's the only person
who can bring those people together.
And I think we underrate those figures
because it's harder to tell stories
about being a great manager.
And if you are, maybe that's
actually his talent in organizing this.
But we don't like to tell that story
about him, and we'd like to paint
it more as a genius.
Yeah. Has he had. Yeah.
Has he had any of the individual ideas or
made any of the individual breakthroughs?
Well, you could say one thing.
He's done it space-x
very successfully say
I want to use the cheapest possible parts.
I want these rockets to be reusable.
I just want to change the entire idea
of what it means to go to space.
I think I give him credit for that.
But yeah, you're right.
He you know, from everything we know
about how he runs his companies,
he is both incredibly
inspiring to work for,
but also manic.
And people love it for a bit
and then they hate it.
You know, and
I think that's kind of fascinating is that
the kind of relentless work
ethic again, it's bittersweet.
It's giving you something and taking
something people kind of like you.
And lots of Silicon Valley companies
have the air of a kind of cult,
and you join the cult and people
get a huge sense of meaning and purpose.
They're doing something extraordinary,
and it's
putting extraordinary demands on them.
But sometimes they come out
the other side of that experience
feeling absolutely battered.
I'm not sure.
Maybe you can't
have one without the other.
And I think the.
Guy, maybe what makes him
more exceptional is the fact
that he's not just two weeks old.
Right?
Building stuff in the world.
There's a great exchange between him
and the tech investor, Paul Graham, about
why maybe Elon Musk might be better at,
you know,
you might be better at building hardware,
which is interesting than software,
because actually, the big companies
in Silicon Valley for the last decade
or so have
mostly been software companies,
the ones that people are excited about.
Whereas, you know,
you think of the technical achievement
of space X of Tesla
and of something like Apple.
You know, Apple is
one of the richest companies in the world,
but that is based around
having an incredibly good supply
chain, actually.
Has it come out
with the kind of groundbreaking products
of the Steve Jobs era recently?
I arguably know what it is incredibly
good is making stuff.
And again, that's the kind of genius
that gets underrated in comparison to
conceptual genius.
Yeah.
That's interesting.
I could I feel the government is milk.
I think you might.
And there that you don't have to like it's
the things they are doing are like space
ish is like totally amazing with the
yeah machines that they're like,
but we can see that there's, there's
not someone, there's not a person
that you can see that achievements.
It's like a team effort.
Everybody knows that.
I remember people saying at NASA that,
you can be a leader.
We tell people that I have to put
a man on the moon, that kind of stuff.
That's, But those are like,
harder stories to mythologize, I guess.
Yeah. And that's why the word mess
is in the title of the book.
And because it's not there
to say that genius doesn't exist,
it's fair to say that it's a story,
and it's a story that we tell ourselves,
and it's got the qualities of a story.
That's the that's maybe because of
why is genius.
I mean.
Because, I mean, in the sense
of mythology, like Greek mythology,
it's a set of stories
about how we understand the world.
And it's not reality.
It's reality curved into, a method
that's palatable that that appeals to us.
You know, I think stories go undergo
a form of evolution by natural selection.
And I write about this in the book
they go through, you know,
when you hear the story of Picasso,
it gets told and retold and retold
and it kind of achieves
its final perfect form in the in the form
that is most satisfying to us.
And so, you know,
the people get hailed as geniuses.
They very often have a kind of caricature
of themselves that becomes famous.
Anyone who's becomes
famous will tell you that,
you know, it's quite a bruising experience
to find out that there's just
a weird, shaved off version of yourself
walking around out there
that people have strong opinions on,
but that definitely happens to genius.
We boil geniuses
down to a few kind of key essentials,
and that's the that's the mythology.
And also
we want that because it's easier
to have like a person or a face
to a certain idea or a certain industry
or a certain movement
than to have like a whole complex picture
of the whole idea of the whole movement.
Yeah.
And also it becomes a referendum
on whether or not you like it or not.
If I, you know, you and I can have
a very complicated conversation about AI
and frontier AI models and whether or not
we think that ultimately going to be good
for humanity above humanity, but that
that conversation is much easier to have
if we have it through.
Do you like what grok the ex
AI model is doing?
On on the ex service.
Do you like what do you think Sam
Altman is a visionary or is he a salesman?
Do you think Elon Musk is a genius
or a maniac or or both,
you know, or charlatan, right?
Actually, there's a lot of people
who will say to you
that, you know, Elon Musk
is is a charlatan.
So you you become kind of proxies, right?
They become aware of having a big,
complicated argument
boil down to one person essentially.
And that's a
that's a really useful function
that geniuses play in our society.
And there wouldn't be any,
y, why do people want to talk about these?
It's always fun to talk about people
who are weird,
and unusual and exciting, don't you think?
I mean,
I write in the book about the fact that,
you know,
I say I love the paintings of Van
Gogh, and I'm just.
There's something about looking at them
that just provokes
this huge emotion to me.
I don't know how.
I don't know how they exist.
You know, that, William Gibson line
that any sufficiently advanced technology
is indistinguishable from magic.
I think that's how we feel about geniuses.
It's. It's magic, isn't it?
Just seeing some the fact that someone
was able to do that is extraordinary.
But, you know, the thing that you use, van
Gogh is an example.
He very successfully married
Post-Impressionist painting
and the techniques
that have come out of Impressionism
with his own influences
from Japan and Japanese woodblock prints.
And that doesn't undermine his talent.
And doing those things,
it makes the, you know,
makes the story to me
much more interesting.
But he sits at the collision
of two artistic traditions.
You could say the same thing
about Picasso.
He is an extremely good
conventional artist in his early years.
Then he becomes influenced
by African masks
and, and and by so-called primitive art.
And he paints the, you know,
Moselle d'Avignon,
which is his big Cubist breakthrough.
He sits at the kind of collision
of two traditions.
And that's not to say, you know, I'm
not by saying that.
I'm not saying Picasso wasn't talented,
incredibly talented.
I'm just saying
it's it's a more interesting
to look at him and his influences.
But we don't tend to do that.
We want we want the breakthrough.
And, you know, Would you say that makes,
would you say that it makes
the picture of the genius
more rich and more interesting?
I mean, I like it
more some people find it,
some people find it an attack.
I think they find that if you say someone
was heavily influenced by someone or,
you know, here's this, you know, pre
figuration of their work somewhere else,
they feel like you're, you're saying that
the other that person that they love,
you know, wasn't amazing, that they were
they were cheap or they were copying.
I feel a bit like a little bit
someone reading a book.
I had this feeling,
something that you just said and
I wasn't like,
I really like the conclusion.
But at some, some passages
I had the same feeling where I was like,
like you were demystifying something that
I held wholly, or you know what I mean?
Like, yeah, yeah, yeah. Like.
This is not entirely,
not comfortable.
Yeah, maybe.
Yeah, I think,
but I think that's really interesting.
I don't know about you,
but I'm always interested in the things
that make me uncomfortable
and trying to understand what that is.
And I think I also think
that I can understand that happening now
in the wake of the decade
that we've just lived through,
where I think there was a lot of giant
killing and people were told,
I'm sorry, you can't like the movies
of Woody Allen anymore.
You can't like the Art of Picasso anymore.
You know, you can't like, go, go
because he spent time
in the South Pacific, you know,
you hear these people that you like.
You're not allowed to like them anymore
because they were bad people.
And I think there's been a backlash
to that, you know, and I and
I think it was a it was an unfair thing
to ask of people, if you really love
whatever it might be, if you really love
Annie Hall or Manhattan,
you don't have to sign off
on thinking that you know, everything
that Woody Allen does is amazing.
But people kind of
don't want that taken away from them.
I talked to someone who,
had a Michael Jackson song at her wedding.
She walked down the aisle
to Michael Jackson
and about how it felt to her
when the allegations of sex abuse
came out against him,
and the fact that now
something that meant so much to her,
you know, her wedding, her,
you know, one of the best days of her life
had this kind of like asterisk
next to it
that it was kind of contaminated by,
you know, by this, this whole discussion.
And I can understand
why people don't want things
that they love taken away from them.
You know, there's a big reaction
when it turns out that you get these
rediscovery, reappraisal of artists
or scientists, where we find out
that about their feet of clay
because people don't want that, you know,
I think
it happens in science as well as the arts.
You know, if you have a hero that you grow
up, and, you know, you worship them,
it's a bit like the process
where I think for teenagers,
when they find out that their parents
aren't kind of all knowing that,
that they can offer me
this intense disappointment.
But then hopefully you get
to the adult stage where you think
it's quite hard to be a parent.
They did their best
and and you forgive them.
And I think that's sort
of the adult version of where
you need to get to with hero worship,
which is I can accept that this person
wasn't perfect.
That doesn't affect
the things that I admire about them,
all the things that they produced
that I really like.
And part of it is that we actually
want them to be imperfect,
that we need genius to be imperfect.
Right. That's interesting.
What do you mean by that?
Well, they need to be flawed.
They need to be tormented.
They need to be. That's like what?
Why do you like them in the first place?
Or maybe not.
Why do you like it?
But those are
the stories that stand out amongst.
The stories of struggle.
Definitely the stories of genius
that stand out most.
And I think that's quite moving too,
because, you know,
I write in the book about Stephen Hawking,
who I think is a very good example.
You know, the physicist who had ALS
and progressive muscular dystrophy,
essentially, which put him in a wheelchair
and by the end was only able
to communicate by blinking his eyes,
but was contemplating these incredibly
difficult questions of physics.
And I think there's something about that
that is just mystical to us
that you would keep
striving and overcoming.
But if you read the work
of other physicists,
they will talk about how
that was quite uncomfortable.
The kind of celebrity cult around him
wasn't necessarily
good for his physics work. Probably not.
But it made him into a celebrity
in the way that his contemporaries,
somebody like Roger Penrose,
just just wasn't.
And there's a related version of that,
which is that
you want people to be interesting.
I mean, that sounds very obvious,
but it's been very difficult for,
people to reclaim geniuses about whom
we don't know
a great deal about their biography
because there is no mythology.
You can't build a sort of story
about that.
You know,
there's just there's just the work.
I think, and the controversy is
what makes them interesting.
And then I think maybe that's what I had
when I was reading this or that was like
feeling like that was being taken away.
I just did it was taking a away and and
being able to like,
where people just don't.
You should definitely like, wait,
I mean, I'm quite a weird person.
I'm pro weird
people is a concept generally.
And I think one of the things
that's really beautiful
about reading the story of genius is that
you find that lots of people who are
very different and find it very hard
to accommodate themselves to society,
nonetheless achieve incredible things.
My first book was about feminism.
It was called Difficult Women,
and it was built around
this idea of difficulty, the idea
that if you want to change the world,
you have to be
it kind of at right angles to it.
You can't if you're somebody who is,
you know, grown up, very comfortable,
you're happy with the political situation
that you live in.
Life is working out really well for you.
You don't become a revolutionary.
You become a revolutionary
because there's something in you
that says this isn't right.
And you're also the kind of itchy,
obsessive, you know, difficult person
that is willing to stake their life
on, on making this change.
And I think that's the other thing.
I find very many of those similar types
come out in this book.
You find somebody like Isaac Newton,
you know, just a very fundamentally weird
but brilliant man.
And and those two things are indivisible.
The bit where I think it's
dangerous is the bit
where we say that people who aren't weird,
therefore aren't,
you know, aren't geniuses.
The idea that if you're well-adjusted
so, you know, it's boring.
And I think that's
that's a kind of fetishization of oddness
which doesn't necessarily help
the old people themselves,
that they have to be special
in order to get the kind of pass
for just being a bit different.
And they have to gradually
and they have to
gradually start acting more and more.
Well, I think celebrity does that.
Fame does that to anybody anyway. Yeah.
I don't think anybody I don't think any.
Does anyone become more normal
after they become famous?
I can't really think of anyone.
Some of them become special
because they stay at home.
That that in itself is.
Yeah.
That's being that's that's the most
unusual thing to be Paul McCartney.
And still to be saying after 60 years
is one of the most famous
people in the world,
is an underrated achievement.
And, would you say area of society
and maybe the type of work or the art
that the genius has changed over time,
maybe you could you take us through
the evolution of what we consider genius?
Yeah.
I mean,
I think one of the foundational texts
and I write about it in the, in the book
is Giorgio Vasari's Lives of the artists.
And he had the who I had of great fortune
and a great misfortune.
His great fortune
was to be alive at the time where
some incredible artists were working.
So, Titian, just after Michelangelo,
Leonardo da Vinci.
I like this a bit, where I go into things
of thinking that the Ninja Turtles.
Donatello. Raphael.
But, you know,
so they had that, you know, in terms
of writing about the artist
who were working at his time,
what a time to be alive.
The great tragedies that he wasn't.
He was a he was a fine artist.
He was a mediocre, not mediocre,
was definitely a good artist,
but he wasn't Michelangelo.
And that must be it must be tough.
But he pitched essentially
to one of his aristocratic patrons
the idea of writing a group biography
of the lives of the artists.
And he did.
And it's where we get the idea,
really, of the Renaissance
from is the fact that he said,
look at all these people at the same time,
doing the same thing.
And so you can almost trace to him that
that idea of the genius,
the Renaissance genius.
And so, so when you say you would start
us, we started out
with the Renaissance man.
Yeah. A Renaissance man. Oh, yeah. Yeah,
I have the American.
Yeah. Right.
Started out
with, with the Renaissance man.
And from there I was geniuses. Oh.
Yeah.
So yeah,
I think you get during the Renaissance,
the artist,
you know, who is, and and the
the word renaissance is,
is rebirth.
So it's about going back
to classical principles, and rediscovering
that tradition.
So that's baked into the idea of genius
that you are.
You know, this is a movement
that is doing something to art.
Then you move on to the I think the next
significant shift is the Romantics.
And I'm thinking
lots of the English poets in Byron Keats,
words, sorry, were the, for example,
being a, you know,
an important text there,
the idea of a tortured genius,
the poet really is
that is the kind of becomes the,
I think
Shelley calls the poets the unacknowledged
legislators of the world.
You know, the idea that these people write
writing sonnets about,
you know, bees or whatever it might be,
are actually changing the culture
in some way, which just we just
don't feel like that now about poetry.
We just don't.
We have to be tormented.
And they have to be tormented
because it is about the fact that, again,
you you've been given something, but you,
you know, there's a cost to it, too.
And I don't think you can
weirdly tell that story without reference
to tuberculosis,
which sounds like a very weird thing
to say, but it is the romantic disease.
Susan Sontag writes about this in illness
as a metaphor.
She writes about a difference
between the way that cancer is seen and,
tuberculosis or consumption,
as it would have been called,
because it's a disease that, you know,
you become very pale, you cough up blood,
you know, for men, it makes you sort of
more feminine in the sense of being weak.
These are the kind of archetypes of people
hang around it.
So there's this really weird line
from Byron where he says,
you know, I sort of,
I wish I had consumption.
It would be, wouldn't it
be much more romantic if I did,
if I was suffering in this, this way?
And so, yeah, the idea was that
that suffering brought you closer
to art,
to transcending being human, essentially.
And then I think, you know, in the 1900s,
maybe you move into this idea
more of the mechanical genius.
You know, this is the kind of age of
industrial, like, hyper industrialization.
Somebody like, Thomas Edison,
the American inventor becomes incredibly
important to America's mythology.
So, yeah, sure.
Europe had all these the old masters, you
know, this was this is the old continent.
But here we're America
when you we're making stuff,
Edison is called the
American Prometheus, you know, after
the guy who stole fire from the gods.
So this is the idea that, you know,
America is just
is is forging the future,
and it's people, it's inventors
who are now the idea of genius.
And that mutates into the 20th century
dominant form of genius to me, anyway,
which is the kind of tech genius
which is a human who is has things
in common with a computer.
You know, they are incredibly good
at maths or engineering.
They make things that are,
again, futuristic.
But the price of that might be that
maybe they are socially awkward.
You know, the nerds essentially,
that kind of nerd genius is
is our dominant form.
And I think that's
I think that's still where we are today.
I'm kind of fascinated to know
what the next archetype will be,
but I genuinely don't don't know.
Is this,
you know, it's it's like, okay.
Yeah,
yeah, it's the culture was there.
It's.
I know you just said, you don't.
Know, I don't know, I really don't know.
But but,
maybe we can try to.
Okay. Weird. Very good.
Good brains.
If you see, like, our culture right now,
the tech rose,
the tech geniuses, they've been,
causing a lot of headlines in.
They're from the first
in our administration.
I think the last century.
You with the word genius.
We think of Einstein now.
I think people think of you a
of those kinds of, tech, CEOs.
Would you what would you hope
that our culture shifts in terms of,
calling people.
To just go outside?
So I'm all right.
So just silent, like.
I think that's.
Someone who's right, I said.
Yeah.
I'm sorry.
And so, You
the fire next door?
Well, okay. Yeah.
Let me pick up on that. Yeah.
I think what's interesting about the
AI companies
is that way that they often
talk about their models,
they talk about them as geniuses,
which is really interesting.
You know, one of the things
that's not necessarily surprised me,
but I think has been very obvious,
is that people treat ChatGPT
or Claude or whatever
the name of the model is as a person.
And actually,
if you think if you if you read the way
that PSA people are anthropic
talk about Claude, which is their model,
they do talk about it.
Is this kind of quasi divine
being that they're kind of
in the same room with, I think there's a
we have an innate tendency
to anthropomorphize,
to see things as human,
even when they're not.
And I think that's something
that I've definitely seen
with with AI models, both from the users
and from the people who work with them,
who know the most closely.
Right?
You end up,
you start off by giving something a name,
and then before long you're worrying
about hurting its feelings,
which isn't a bad impulse at all.
But I you know,
I wonder if if we're now treating them,
you know, do we treat ChatGPT as a genius?
Essentially. Will they be?
When the
AI models become the next genius AI?
It's not that old an idea, really,
because they have many of the qualities
of a genius, right?
Which is that they're sort of superhuman.
And we can't really understand
how they do what they do,
which is two great qualities of, you know,
about a great scientific discovery
or a brilliant painting.
All right.
You don't know how anyone you couldn't do
it, you don't know how anyone else
could have done it.
That's also how I feel about,
you know, about Claude, essentially.
Like what?
What is the thinking going on
here is the matching.
What is it?
So I think there's that.
The other side of it is
I wonder whether or not in a world
where computing power is so vast,
we move back to human experiences
and we value them highly.
You know.
Before we go, yeah.
But I was thinking
when you said the last thing,
they're also,
they're also actually socially quite.
Yeah, yeah. Well, yes.
In the opposite way to, to to tech browse.
I guess the myth of the tech, bro,
is that basically,
you know, you can't make eye contact,
don't know how to talk to girls.
And the problem
is a lot of the aim of AI models
is that they tend towards
being incredibly sycophantic.
Like, great idea, well done. You.
But yeah, in both cases it took.
Like somebody read.
Yeah to interact with people,
but yeah, you know how to do it.
But that's I think both of those are kind
of artifacts of the computer age that we,
we know so much of our lives
now, but our relationship with computers
and computing power that either
some people pride themselves
on thinking like computers
or we're interested in computers
trying to be human.
But, you know, the the kind of the side
effects of superabundance are fascinating,
which is that
what will people pay money for now?
They'll pay for experiences,
the things that are booming.
You know, I want to go on holiday
to the place I've seen on Instagram
and take a photo of me in front of my,
Fuji, you know, and have been there.
I want to go to Taylor Swift's concert
with 2 million
other people, and I'll pay
hundreds of pounds to do that.
You know, in a, you know,
you can listen to dinosaur songs
on Spotify for, you know, 0.0001 pence.
It's about now what are the things
that there's only a limited amount of,
you know, art.
You know,
I thought the theater would have
a real trouble bouncing back after Covid.
You know, it's it's struggled
in some senses, but one of the things
it's reliably generated
sales is having a, a celebrity casting
because there's only, you know,
there's only one Cynthia Erivo and you're
either in the room with Harry or not,
and people will pay an enormous
amount of money for that
because by definition, humans are limited.
Whereas we're now used to this world
of the internet and AI, which is just a,
you know, there's more stuff
than you could ever consume in a lifetime.
Yeah.
And think maybe the the
idea of the struggle is hard to imagine.
Also with a lack of food. Right.
I think is a great study about,
poetry written by AI
in which people actually,
when they were blind, tested on it.
They really liked AI written poetry,
but as soon as they found out
it was written by an AI,
they downgraded it again and again.
It's a defense of what do you want?
You want a human connection.
You want the fact that there's
only so much of something
that someone has to give.
You want a sense of connecting
with a human brain?
I think there's a there's
a quite a long bit in the book about
Hans Eisenach, who wrote a book on genius,
had this idea that the genius
should either die before 30 or after 80.
Really?
And and for the under 30s,
you know, for your Amy
Winehouse, James
Dean, River Phoenix, Keats.
You know,
the idea is that there's something, again,
bittersweet,
that there's not enough of them.
What could they have done? What would the
rest of that life look like?
You have to live to 80 in order
really just to become
the kind of father of the nation
and influence the next generation.
But if you can't do that, then they're
the best things to do is to die young.
So people will, you know,
you were only ever beautiful and perfect
and never disappointing
and middle aged, essentially.
But we'll also will never have enough.
And that's part I think that's part of the
I story, too.
That feeling that everything is
impermanent and limited is so emotional
to humans.
So that will be the other hope
that we try to find genius in
experiences with people. Again.
I yeah, it's a two futures.
Are everybody talking to the AI
and forming kind of cults to worship them
as gods or people go to the park
and hang out with their friends like,
you know, or go to, you know,
a concert hall and listen to music again,
that one of those futures seems a lot
more utopian than the other one.
And is there a type of human genius
that could compete with.
Yeah, I when I was like.
Say, oh,
my life took ages to come
and they might be the next five minutes.
But I found that foundation where you were
okay, a good.
My worry.
Human genius.
Yeah.
So, like, where we can find
a different kind of genius
than the tech world, you know?
I mean, I hope so.
I think, yeah.
I don't know about your relationship
with tech.
Mine is quite conflicted.
I I'm still.
I love things that are new
and interesting.
I'm trying to.
I just downloaded
cloud code and thought, nope,
I don't know what any of this stuff.
You know, I never studied computing, but,
you know, being curious and,
interested in new things
I think is is beautiful.
At the same time, I, like most of us,
wish I spent less time on my phone,
less time.
Doomscrolling
you know, drinking from the firehose,
all of these phrases that we have to say
that you just it's odd to be disconnected
from yourself and so much of life
being mediated through a screen.
So, you know, I wouldn't mind seeing
what the next turn of that wheel is.
Yeah, I think, I think, I think
my relationship with tech is,
yeah, I is ambivalent.
I think in the
way that lots of people's is.
Yeah.
I share the ambivalence.
But it's, it's.
Yeah.
And I don't know,
in our capitalist society right now,
it's really hard to imagine
other people than this
tech bros becoming, being called geniuses.
You find that as well?
Yeah. I think it's very sad that.
I mean, the book is full of geniuses
who all, you know, people
who have been hailed as geniuses,
who have a really difficult relationship
with making money,
and quite often, again, the person
who ends up being called a genius is
the person who's got the best marketing,
which is really difficult, I think.
Is it trying to separate out
true achievement from somebody
who's best at selling themselves
as a product is often very hard.
So, you know, and artists have had this,
you know,
this struggle for, for centuries, right.
When you in if you're an not in
the Renaissance, you had to find a patron,
which meant that you had to paint
very flattering pictures of a medici
or whoever it might be,
then you end up with the marketplace
and you end up with, you know, people like
Andy Warhol or Jeff Koons making art
that's specifically
about, you know, how much,
how reproducible is this?
How much money can I make out of this?
Damien Hirst art is often
very much in dialog with that idea.
You know, he made a skull entirely covered
with diamonds.
That was about the statement of like,
what is, you know,
what is the most expensive thing I could
do to to a dead object, essentially.
So I think, you know,
these are conversations
have been happening for a long, long time.
The relationship between achievement
and money has always been quite tense.
I think it's particularly tense
now, as you say, with
with what's happening in tech,
because there are, you know, the US stock
market is so dominated
by these big tech companies,
you know, and ones that have only existed
often for, you know, 20 years, say,
you know, we are so kind of
there's so much wealth and investment,
you know, really just going to a handful
of companies in a tiny geographical area
in a way that me to me, feels like
making an extremely dangerously large
bet on a very small number of
if kind of horses.
I'm not sure that much was going to tech
horses.
Tech bro
horses, horses made of tech brains.
But you know what I mean.
Like, I would be I would be more relaxed
about tech if I felt that
there was exciting stuff happening in
lots of other ways, but it makes me
it makes me sad to think that it's hard
now because of things
like Spotify, for example,
to make a living as a mid-level artist,
you know, they're all the superstars,
and then it's become harder
for everybody else at the lower levels.
And I think you probably say the same
about the film industry.
You know, you can make extremely expensive
films or very, very low budget ones,
and the mid-tier is as hollowed out,
television, I think.
Well, now the streaming boom is over.
We might have a similar thing.
The same thing happens in science.
If you win the Nobel, your lab is funded.
Things are great, but actually is research
funding for mid-tier scientists.
Is that now tougher?
You know, people are finding
that more difficult to do.
And that is that is a story about the way
that capitalism has shaped our society,
perhaps into ways
that are more when it takes all,
which is not really healthy.
Like I would prefer to have more people
doing things
that they love and a kind of more
rich ecosystem, rather than a couple
of really tall trees that you know,
whose canopy shades everything else.
And maybe also so that, it
drains the talents of potential geniuses
into one sector.
Does it? Yeah.
Yeah. People with.
Yeah.
Tons of people wanted to finance.
Yeah,
yeah.
There's a line from,
the book Chaos Monkeys by a guy
who used to work for Facebook
as something that essentially I've seen
the best minds of my generation,
you know, training people to click on ads.
Right. And that's just that's.
Yeah.
When you think about what Facebook is
as a company, it's an advertising company.
You know, it's
now trying to pivot to be an AI company
because everything, everything is.
But that's not and there's nothing wrong
with advertising per se, but it's not
it doesn't feel as exciting
as building a cathedral
somehow. But,
We spoke to Corey Doctorow.
Yeah.
You know, he says when the company said
they're pivoting, they're being paid.
Right.
And that's
definitely the case with Facebook.
They just were like, I don't think
there's anything in this AI business.
It's fine.
And then they just,
you know, in the salaries they were trying
to poach people on were extraordinary.
You know, like the people talking about
kind of eight figure salaries.
And again, that's a story
about kind of monopolization,
you know, would it be in a world
in which I write about this
in the book, you know, in 110 years,
brief Facebook, no matter
boom, WhatsApp, Instagram, Oculus,
you know, just,
just everything being sucked into this,
into these giant mega corporations again.
Is that the best use of individual
people's talents just to be kind of,
you know, one cog in a giant machine,
I again, I would I'd be more happy
if there was if they were,
if they were more interesting companies.
And you didn't have to just rely on scale.
Maybe that's also the way things.
Appear.
If you understand that Mark Zuckerberg is
maybe also an example of someone
who's actually proven, scaling up
and not really inventing stuff.
He's not an inventor.
His genius is just based on right
companies
at the right time
and, you know, puts them out there.
And then also everybody, starts
using them.
Yeah.
His fundamental insight is, shouldn't
I have a website where you can rate
how hot people are?
And, you know, I'm old enough.
I remember that another website
that that there was
a more overt version of that
which was called Hot or not.com, but,
you know, but Mark Zuckerberg is
an interesting example of the genius myth.
I don't write about him
so much in the book, but the, the film,
Aaron Sorkin's
brilliant film Social Network, directed
by David Fincher, is really interesting
because it makes one very big change
to Mark Zuckerberg's life, which is that
in real life, he started dating Priscilla
Chan, his wife of 20 years, at college.
By all accounts, you know, very happy.
They've got three kids together.
The book makes him a single loser.
And that's really interesting to me
that they would think that that story is,
you know, let's make the creation of this
incredibly big website and social network
platforming about one guy's quest
to, like, make girls like him.
And turns out you got a girl to like him.
That was not a problem.
But it is his.
Yeah, he was with the same woman that he's
been married to now for a long time
when he was, you know, during all this,
you know, this is not a guy
who is driven by his, like, resentment
at not being able to get laid.
But that was a very powerful genius
myth of the nerd
loser who gets his revenge on the world.
And the tagline for that movie is,
you know, you can't get to
whatever it was a billion friends
without making some enemies.
So it was all about him
being kind of opposed to the world.
And if he's just a normal regular guy
with who's not massively tortured,
it doesn't doesn't really work.
Of course, the good thing
about Mark Zuckerberg is that with fame,
he has had a chance to get more weird,
and he's now obsessed with Roman emperors.
And this guy named all of his daughters
after various Roman emperors.
And that which is the kind of thing that
I think that's that's what being called
a genius does to you.
You go, that's cool.
My kids after Roman emperors.
He started off as a stable genius.
Yeah, very stable genius.
And, well, I'm,
you know, I but I think that I think
if you look at biopics, they are really
interesting as a way of understanding
how genius may get constructed,
because the social network
both relies on Mark Zuckerberg,
the loser, and Mark Zuckerberg versus
these two in the Winklevoss twins, Blythe,
you know, bastions of privilege.
These guys who are just from, you know,
who've just a handsome and tall
and have got everything going for them.
And he's the nerd and the outsider.
And for a particular type of guy
at the time,
that was that was the mythology of tech.
It was when you were in high school,
there were guys who were the jocks
and they got all the girls, and they were
really handsome and they played football.
And you went to computer club
and no one liked you.
And but guess what?
Now you're incredibly rich
and you can have anything you want.
And that's. Essentially films.
Revenge of the. Nerds, right?
But that's that.
That is the kind of mythology
and that's been a very durable mythology,
despite the fact now that
there are a lot of extremely rich nerds,
being a nerd is a really great thing.
Like, any parent would be quite happy for
that kid to go to computer club, right?
But that's fine.
That's not you know, being the jock is not
this sort of socially
like pinnacle anymore.
And if you were, I'm going
to try to ask the question one more time.
Just to
if you could point to one side of it,
maybe it's poets
and it's people working with dogs,
I don't know, but if you would have like
one type of person that could be annoying
to the new geniuses
instead of tech world, who would you pick?
We'll see.
You put your poking my at my actual unease
with the label of genius here,
which is that, you know,
I would love to to
I would love to find better ways.
And I think this is a huge challenge
as a writer
to talk about the genius of teams
or the genius of organizations.
And we do have some examples of that.
People in tech circles will talk to you
endlessly about Bell Labs,
run by telecommunications company
in the 20th century,
just to sort of huge
amounts of innovations.
They will talk to you about what
it's like, how amazing
it is to work in a creative team
with other people.
And, you know my background,
I'm a journalist.
I have been so happy throughout my career
to work in incredible teams,
because you can always achieve more
together than you can just as one person.
You need people to sparkle.
Yeah.
And I've always throughout
my career had editors who have said,
this goes on a bit long.
Could you make this shorter?
I don't understand what you're saying
here.
You know, that kind of that kind of input
is great, but also lots of,
creativity happens in pairs.
I'm just about to go and talk about
John and Paul, the Beatles,
you know, two incredible songwriters,
but together just,
a force much great
an who could have been on their own.
And we've got a little bit better
at telling those stories, but
I think instead of us trying to find
a new archetype of genius, I'd probably
be happier if we could broaden out
the ways that we talk about achievement,
to talk about the genius of groups
and teams.
I mean, and as I'm saying that it sounds
phenomenally boring.
It's going to be quite the challenge.
I'm not sure. Maybe it could be done.
I think it's a different way
of telling a story that's the problem is
we we're so used to the other story. Yeah.
Yeah.
And so
it's a it will take experimentation.
But we've been used to the other story
since, you know, Norse mythology and,
you know, Beowulf and Roman
and Greek mythology.
So I think that more might just appeal
to human brains more.
I think we might have to concede
that point.
Yeah.
My kids
keep asking me to tell stories about
singular heroes doing stuff.
Yeah.
They don't want to ever hear
about Bell Labs.
I don't see many children's books
among the great teams.
Well, yeah.
I haven't felt like, the
a bit.
They have those books.
Now there's the only good books, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, yeah. They're like little people.
Big dreams. Yeah. And then they'll.
And then you have to perseverance
and then, you know, and everybody
super enthused all that kind of stuff.
But they're always
just you feel that there's a meaning.
There's like some.
Oh that they're teaching you. Yeah.
Put into the book.
And you somehow,
you don't feel that, if you read like,
the children's version
that you want to see yourself.
Yeah. People are. Actually.
Oh, this is a this is actually
a great leader of this team as well.
You it what we also as a team.
It's very 18th century.
The 18th century had a craze
what they called, conduct books,
moralizing literature like by Hannah Moore
was one of the biggest selling books.
And they were essentially kind
of instructional texts.
And we've given kids a version of that
now where we give them books about,
you know, about people who've overcome
great obstacles in this very heavily
didactic way,
which is fascinating,
because the one thing that children love
more than anything is stories
about like, people farting or the road
doll stories, which are all about people
being naughty, breaking the law,
poisoning their grandmother.
You know, all these things
that are kind of decadent.
But, one thing I was fascinated by
when I was researching Thomas
Edison is the fact that he is now
a genius for American children.
And I read about the fact that almost
no one visits the museum in Menlo
Park, his laboratory, and someone I know
wrote to me saying, yeah, I went to it.
I went to to it,
and it was the way to go and it was empty.
And so he has become a kind of
children's story essentially about.
And the way that it's raised with him
is that, you know, the 99% perspiration,
1% inspiration,
the idea that you just got to work hard.
So he, you know, his his genius
myth has now moved from American
Prometheus to kind of grind set you know,
you've just got to get up in the morning
and try 100 things,
and one of them all will work.
The great sadness, actually, you should.
Maybe that's like a
it will be like a shift from the
the genius
in our culture.
Maybe we're slowly shifting towards.
Yeah. You don't you think I.
Was the driver. Yeah.
Which is probably healthier, right.
Because everybody could probably stand
to try a little bit harder.
But what you can't do
is be a savant, right?
You're just not born playing the piano
at the level
that Mozart could when he was five.
But you could, you know, you could try it.
You could find something
that you enjoy doing,
you think you're good at
and try really hard at it.
But that is interesting about though
we though we, we fetishize
the kind of lightning bulb moment,
you know, the strike of inspiration.
You will often find many,
many people who achieve great things
who just grind away
that they work really hard. But,
and David
Gunnarsson has this idea
of two different types of innovator
or genius, which is the kind of the kind
of which he is.
He references Picasso and Suzanne
Picasso has this idea. Cubism, right?
What if painting.
But I'll make it look a bit like blocks
where Suzanne works and works away
at the same subject.
He will have paints the same things.
He's just trying to make the best version
of this
ideal version of a painting
that's in his head,
and that's you know, and you can see
the difference between those two types
of, of genius,
even in how much their art costs.
You know, with with Picasso,
people want to buy the Cubist work.
They want to buy the art.
The idea with Suzanne, the value persists
until his much later work
because it's about iteration.
It's about doing the same thing.
It's about perfecting.
And I think that that is two fundamentally
different ideas about genius.
Is it the Big bang or is it the
somebody who has a kind of life's work
and an a perfect image in their head?
They're working towards,
Thank you.
It's that.
If I, I warn you, I.
Don't know,
but I, part of what I would like to do
is also talk about some of these,
times.
Yeah.
Other, other types of
will find themselves geniuses.
But I think I would like to do that.
Stand. Sure.
Yeah.
You thought they were part of.
I really didn't talk talking.
That's pretty funny,
I did.
I think this this overcoat,
I think is peak romantic genius, isn't it?
The kind of great coat that if you've just
kind of leapt off your horse
to be part of your grand
tour across Europe?
It's very.
It's a really,
like a German romantic long it is.
It really is.
Like he's just gone
to the kind of ruined gothic castle
in which he's about to meet a flighty
young woman in a night dress.
Hard to imagine.
Donald Trump is an 18th century
romantic genius.
I would say
writing poetry.
Maybe you could,
start going by some of them and then.
Okay.
Pick one
and you can take them off another.
Maybe.
I thought there's some of these
kind of labels, right, that you have.
Like you, you say, some people are,
Like, millennial boy child.
What can I say?
Yeah. Okay. What's that?
Come behind.
So, I'm a big fan of 18th century.
Ellen.
I'm not sure what he is
supposed to have done immediately
before this portrait, but,
I guess he looks a bit like he's,
I don't know, sailed down the Danube
or something
in an attempt
to write his great work about.
Yeah, I don't know, mathematics
or something like that.
That would be very kind
of 18th century thing to do.
Van Gogh looks,
brilliant in this.
I think one of things
that's fascinating about Van
Gogh from portraits
is that he's managed to get his.
He managed to mythologize his own hair.
You always see Van Gogh hair like that.
And I think he did a really good job of
of making the case that he had great hair.
Donald Trump, I struggle to say,
is a 19th century romantic genius.
I don't think he seems enormously tortured
about anything at all.
He's a kind of exemplar, I guess.
I'm a very 1980s kind of genius,
which is just the kind of bullying
salesman, that was a very popular
kind of 80s archetype.
And then. Yeah.
Mark Zuckerberg had looks every bit
the kind of,
I don't know, whatever the 18th century
equivalent is of the millennial boy king
supposedly had been born in.
I guess if he was born in like 1783,
he would have just been around for,
the American, the, the aftermath,
the American Revolution.
He could have been a young American
or over to Europe on his grand tour.
But, you know, this is what's interesting
about this to me is the fact that you can
you can see so many of the tropes of,
of heroic portraiture and all of these.
Right, which is the kind of noble gaze
off into the distance is if you're having
a particularly big thought,
you know, the kind of the tempestuous
landscape behind you that reflect your,
your personal feelings,
which is the pathetic fallacy.
And there's there's torment.
There's too many. Eyes.
And in the landscape.
I'm not sure there's torment
in, Donald Trump's eyes.
He looks like he's going to buy that ship
and possibly knock down
this Roman forum and, like,
turn it into the Trump branded forum.
But the rest of them, certainly.
Yes, I think so.
If you have some of these archetypes,
like the tortured rebel, the millennial
boy King, you have a bunch of these
kind of like archetypes in the book.
What if you start on the right
when you can pick up the painting
if you want, but maybe just say,
what kind of genius
are we looking at here?
So Elon Musk, I would say,
is the archetype of the kind of tech bro
who is too busy
and important to be nice to you.
And this is kind of a fascinating thing,
I think, which is that
the fact
that you really essentially the rudeness
or the lack of interpersonal skills
is rewritten as evidence of greatness.
You know, he simply is too busy having
big thoughts about rockets to answer.
Well, to send anything other than
like a poop emoji back to you in emails.
Vincent van Gogh, to me,
is the archetype of the tortured genius
that a lot of that mythology is fair
in the sense that he struggled all
his life with mental illness.
You know, he
he killed himself at the age of 37,
having sold only a single painting.
This painting, I've have to say,
this is not a.
This is not a Mankoff. Painting.
He would you do made that landscape
much meaner and darker.
But you know, his sister in law, Jo Van
Goff, Bangor.
She, lived in this boarding house.
I think he was in Utrecht, actually,
which was just entirely covered
in every single, pretty much
every single extant piece of and of art.
They had, almond blossom above the
fireplace in the, in the baby's bedroom.
And she did an enormous service to him
by publishing Van Gogh's,
letters to his brother Theo,
which were all about his struggle,
his inability to sell anything, his need
for money, his mental health struggles.
And that created this incredibly powerful
mythology of the struggling artist,
which was so important to, you know,
how people now interpret the paintings.
You would say.
He would say she, his sister in law,
actually made him, she went to Jeannie.
She made him famous. She made him famous.
She did all the things
that you really need someone to do.
You know, if you are a dead genius.
Which is? She looked after the archive.
She didn't sell off the paintings
too quickly.
She tried to place them in museums.
She created a market for them,
and she created this
really powerful mythology around them.
You know, these were beautiful,
but twisted paintings from a beautiful
but twisted mind.
And ever since,
that has just the thing that has affected
the way that we read Bank of paintings.
You don't look at Van Gogh paintings
and think of them often.
The emotion you get from
them is happiness, and that is that.
Is that right, or is that you reading them
through his biography?
If you look at the irises and, you know,
if you didn't know anything about Van
Gogh, you might think that's
a really happy, colorful painting.
And so a temptation is always to read
the painting through the tortured genius.
Donald Trump is the
is I going to say, the political genius,
the very stable genius?
He certainly thinks he's a genius.
I mean, the the case for Donald Trump,
not something you hear that
much in Europe these days is that he is
a singular historical figure.
He has an analysis of what you know
is wrong with America
and how to make America great again.
And he's managed to get people
to come along with that, that vision,
you know,
and I think probably this is going to send
some of these things, people
gonna laugh at me for saying,
I think people will probably see him
on the level of importance of a
of a Napoleon.
That's the that's the
of all the people I could compare them to.
That's maybe the most flattering,
but in the sense
that American history is different
because he existed in a way that you can't
always say about political leaders.
And finally, Mark
Zuckerberg, the millennial boy king.
He's about my age.
So, yeah, yeah, I was think.
I was sort of feel a bit. Like,
how's he doing?
How rich is he now?
How much better is his life
going than mine?
Oh, good. Still, still very rich.
Is that part of the mythology
like the comparison with us mere mortals?
I think for people who get very famous
and successful, very young,
it is because you think, hang on a minute,
you're 23 and you've done this.
And that becomes another element of the
the kind of superhuman nature of
what's happening
is it's impressive to build a website
that is worth $1 billion.
It's even more impressive to do it
when you're 20,
you know,
when you just dropped out of Harvard.
And for a long time. Yeah.
Mark Zuckerberg's youth was kind of,
you know, it was the thing that he would
wear the Adidas slides,
he wore tracksuit bottoms.
He didn't wear a suit.
You know,
there was very much that he remade that
Silicon Valley mythology
of the kind of the casual ness of it.
You know, this is not buttoned up
establishment.
These guys are young and hip and cool.
Of course, you know,
lots of them are now in the 40s and 50s.
It's quite it's harder.
So he's had his reinvention now as a kind
of jujitsu bro with his gold chain.
And talking about how he doesn't
drink caffeine.
But again, that isn't that is
a very Silicon Valley archetype, right?
Doing the martial arts,
talking about being masculine again, he's,
you know, he he's not immune to fashion,
even though you think
one of the best things
about being a billionaire
is that you don't have to follow fashion,
but people people still do it.
He was the black T-shirt guy, right?
Yeah, exactly.
He just had, like,
loads and loads of the same outfit.
And again,
this was part of his genius mythology.
He was simply too busy and important
to think about
wearing different types of clothing.
He just wore the same thing every day.
And that was one less decision,
because he just got to save his brain
for making the really big decisions.
You have your eye line.
Yeah, yeah, I think a few.
Sorry.
Is there nothing else
to say about any of them?
I think that's maybe it.
Yeah, maybe.
Because maybe you can take his picture.
Tell me a little bit more. About what?
What what a millennial working
and feels. What?
It's just a nightmare.
Maybe you want to put a different
label on him. That's also fine.
No, no, I think.
I think he's I think what Mark Zuckerberg
is a millennial boy king
because he symbolizes, I think for people,
the irresponsibility of Silicon Valley.
And that's more forgivable when you're
young than when you're in your 40s.
So, you know, when you know, the, the,
that kind of idea of the Silicon Valley
motto of move fast and break things
essentially is a bit more forgivable
in somebody who is young.
Because, you know, that's what
that's what young people do.
Sorry.
I'm staring off into the middle distance
where I'm trying to connect my thoughts.
It's very hard
to think and talk at the same time.
It turns out,
It turns clear to him.
Yeah. I mean, you.
Yeah.
No, no, no, it just made me.
Yeah. Okay.
It looks like you are talking
to someone there.
Okay.
Yeah, I think I think Millennial Boy
King is the epithet
that gets applied to him
because he symbolized what was new in the
2000 and young, in the sense that this was
a time when everything was changing.
People had huge hopes for Facebook
and what it might accomplish
during that time when,
you know
it was going to bring down governments
and of course, the Arab Spring
and all that kind of stuff.
So I think his his youth at the time
was a really big part of that mythology.
And it's maybe why there's been a certain
level of discomfort from him
as he's got older. He's now in his 40s.
What's the mythology now? What?
You know, when you were an aged
boy king, when you're just a king,
that's not quite as cool anymore?
Or somehow, is it?
It's not a myth.
It's not all
those different types of king.
You can become the Henry
the Eighth, you know, you can become.
The old, fat, bloated. King.
But I don't think he's, He's very keen
not to do that. I would say,
I think can go with
maybe a little bit more of a
could you take Elon Musk all right.
Yeah.
Because I think we talked about him
also in the interview quite long.
So sure.
Jordan, with the way.
You know, Musk appears in the book.
Quite a lot.
Because he is somebody that people love
to argue about on the internet.
And he's also somebody
I have these very conflicted feelings
about him, too, which is that
he has undoubtedly created
incredibly interesting companies that,
you know, have changed things.
I would say Tesla has done
an incredible job of making electric
cars cool and sexy,
rather than a kind of hair shirt.
You know, you have to have an electric car
because otherwise the seals will be upset.
No, you want an electric car? It's cool.
And that he did that,
with Tesla, with Space-X.
You know, NASA was obviously an incredibly
important and influential organization
in the 20th century.
It had subcontractors
who were seen widely to be quite.
Slow. And expensive.
And he said, I wonder
if we can be much faster and much cheaper,
you know, if we're going to do this thing,
maybe let's have reusable rockets.
Let's try and make all the parts as simple
as they possibly can,
as cheap as they possibly can.
And then we're much more likely to get to,
you know, the Mars or the moon.
And let's not take away
from the achievement.
You know, they have put astronauts
living humans into space in rockets
built by Elon Musk Company.
That is an engineering
feat until, you know,
until Elon Musk came along, that was a
thing that only states could do.
And now private company can do that too.
So I don't you know.
You've seen that one of those.
I did I did.
I went to
Florida and I went to Cape Canaveral.
And I saw everybody
heading for the back of the bay.
So I had no idea what was going on.
And I just so happened that I got there
at the same time
that they were doing a rocket launch.
And it is exactly as awe inspiring
and moving as you would expect it to be.
You will sit on the lawn
and they have the camp dome,
which you've seen in a million films
already, and then just this tiny little
speck of bright orange
appears in the blue blue sky.
And that is, you know, in that case,
that was a cargo payload.
But that's still that stuff
leaving the Earth.
You know, something that if you said
that to a human 2000 years ago
would have sounded like something that
was, you know, only God could have done.
And we can now do it.
And, you know, I did find that I did find
that quite inspiring and moving.
What was it, a moment of genius.
It it it was a
it was certainly a connection
with something that felt superhuman,
which is pretty good definition of genius.
The problem is you go from that.
And my second thought after thinking
this is so inspiring was
why are you on Twitter all day?
You know,
what are you doing with your life?
You can do this.
Why are you arguing with people
on the internet about conspiracy theories
and like replying lol based.
To someone's like meme of a frog.
And I think that's, you know, that's.
Why we love to argue about Elon Musk
is there's two sides of him.
There's the absolute prick side of him,
and there is the side that has done
things that are exceptional.
And as I say in the case of the Rocket,
is absolutely awe inspiring, I think.
So the category that he would fall into
would be like.
Oh, I think it's probably a category
all of his own.
I mean. The asshole genius or like.
Yeah, definitely
the brilliant asshole. Definitely.
But also like the cooked brain genius,
I think as well.
That's the other thing.
I think he had this incredible brain,
but I just wonder if he's just
in a way I couldn't live with it,
you know?
Susie Wiles is the Trump's chief of staff,
talked about his his ketamine use.
You know,
I just wonder whether or not he has
a, a brain that runs very hot
and therefore has been kind of impossible
to to live with, you know, as a child
used to apparently not speak
for quite a long time.
He was very badly
bullied as a child, broke
his nose being pushed down the stairs.
And also grew up in.
Apartheid South.
Africa, which I think is,
you know, it's very difficult to
when you read some of the stuff
that he writes now about race
and intelligence, for example,
you have to remember that
he grew up in a society
that was institutionally, legally racist.
And then the history of race and genius
is a really unpleasant
and uncomfortable one.
And, I'm not surprised that people
who are obsessed with
genius also get obsessed with race
and with with breeding.
I mean, the man's got 14 children
that we know of.
Probably quite happy to have several more.
And that's, again, something that afflicts
people who get called a genius.
They think I must pass on my genius genes,
and that doesn't really exist
as a concept.
You know, I'm
sure his kids will be smart, mostly,
but there's a concept
called reversion to the mean,
which means that whatever
exceptional range of attributes he had,
any kids of his
will be much closer back to normal.
And again, that. Can be a real that can.
Be really upsetting for geniuses.
They assume that they'll have like
a little brood of kind of tiny prodigies,
and they get nice, normal kids.
That anyone else will be very happy. With.
But to them, it's kind of disappointing
because I thought they were going
to found a kind of great lineage.
You hold this for a second and.
It has the exact benefits.
Now that really like in the book
where you compare
the names of his kids with the names,
I mean, Bahamas.
Marie,
I think about Emily. Ben quite a lot.
Just normal people, not Roman.
Look who Romulus.
And, I that's one more question.
If you're you're still popular
when you read them
for the new.
Volume.
A bunch more just shows without talking.
After the show.
Okay, okay.
And that one more so.
Yeah.
Just like in the same scene,
I was thinking,
I just yesterday
I just read somebody saying, like, it
was sort of being a little bit you
at Ellen online and telling him,
why don't you ever post
pictures of nice landscapes
you've seen or beautiful stuff
you've done with your family?
I know, I know, he did a very sad post,
which was like
something like, people tell you
that being rich won't make you happy.
Like, and it was like, I'm proof of that.
And I do think it's sort of essential
tragedy in
life is to be given
everything that you want.
And I think that is his tragedy.
You know,
he obviously had enormously burning
ambition to be a world historical figure.
And again, it's a kind of genius myth
that you well done.
Your a world historical figure, but I
but quite a lot of people hate you
and you can't handle it.
You know, it was very sad reading the
the emails
in the Epstein files about him,
where he's trying to go to the island
and they go, oh, sorry, no,
we won't be there.
And, you know, just to be so successful
and then but
but to still be desperate for people to
like you, I think is kind of fascinating.
But it is it is a classic genius myth.
And what you get is, is talent,
power, success.
What you don't get is the one thing
that you want, which is respect.
So there's there's a price
of your greatness essentially.
And that price is being happy,
which is the one of
maybe one of the most fundamental genius.
Missable.
And you're looking forward to his biopic,
I hope.
I see I feel like Mads
Mikkelsen would play a good, a good Elan.
But yeah, his biopic would be interesting
because
you can see there's
two versions of it, right?
There's the Elan produced and funded
version of it, which is about one,
you know,
child's struggle to overcome their violent
upbringing and make it in America.
And there's the other version,
which is the one
talented man driven mad by the internet.
You know, you can have the rise
or you can have the fall.
So I don't know
which version of the biopic will get.
Maybe a two piece.
Yeah, maybe they like the Beatles.
Well, maybe they can make one person.
Who likes Elon Musk can.
Make one biopic
and but that's that, you know.
That reflects what I write in the book
about the concept of.
Biopics is they're mythmaking.
So you can make the myth of my triumph
over adversity out of the Elon story,
or you can make it mine.
Decline and fall.
How I went mad. The Elon story.
And both of those are.
True to the same degree.
Those are both true about the same person,
but which one you pick to tell
says an enormous amount about you
and how you regard success.
Really.
So that's you know, that's what the genius
myth always is about.
It's about what things do you value?
Do you value
somebody who strove and overcame,
or do you value somebody who's a nice
human being, an individual?
How you go back, you go.
Elon, back. On the.
Mantelpiece where you deserve.
No, if it's okay,
just a few shots of you watching
and just throwing things.
Be discovered.
Explosion victims.
And we have no
okay, brothers.
That's the stable genius, right?
As I say, we're doing a serious. Of.
The my millennial boy came
there is.
When I pedestal and I've been on.
Is that actually a safe place
to end up a pedestal?
Well, it's kind of like that
being put in them all, isn't it?
You know,
someone to look up to,
someone to, to admire.
But also when someone's up on a pedestal,
you can see the for you to for me to say
that is the problem.
The pedestal.
I. Keep thinking if I were going
to find to be what instrument
for quite like
you know on drums went off on bass,
let's sing.
And obviously otherwise make a fuss.
When I make a Tom Hanks at the back.
The greatest supergroup we never had.
To wonder what John would play.
For probably for different genres,
we do have an issue.
I think if you're going to be genius,
you have to you have to really in March
to be very drunk, which is not that you,
when you're in a band.
The two of them were.
In a kind of a band for a little bit.
Right.
Know when Trump.
Oh, so you say you know Mark Zuckerberg.
Yeah. Well yes.
Yes I mean again
the story of genius being one of ego.
It's not a massive surprise to me
that deluge.
The Department
for Governmental Efficiency.
Didn't, didn't work out.
Maybe I should put the next to.
Maybe I should just
go next. Which are actually,
it's the two halves of the American whole.
The American dream.
And I.
Together.
Although I think I think they have them
made it out, but,
Yeah, I think it was very hard
for everybody in the white House.
To work with.
You know, Musk.
Jones chief of staff, describes
him as a, an old, old doc.
But then many geniuses are,
which I thought was very kind.
Description.
Who's not to something your.
I they say
if we did all of this on this style,
we could do the show.
So the the movements will show up.
You could tell if you had.
A favorite, go painting.
I, I recently
listened to a long podcast about his life.
It was actually quite interesting.
Yeah, I like the one with,
the little cafe, and, I think that's cool.
Yeah,
that's one of the latest ones
I heard that was.
Like I said, what I like,
I think, and blossom is my favorite.
It's very simple.
And I like the irises.
His flower paintings are wonderful
because I managed to not be
kind of twee and static
and whatever it might be, but, it's
one of paintings in the National Gallery
I thought, I love so much.
I thought The Prince of Action
and that he's a tree.
I am all right this time.
Actually, I did a cross stitch.
I did an embroidery version of,
sunflowers, which is now my participation.
And let me tell you,
some of the different colors, the others.
You said is here.
But don't you think you said
this here was like a straight line, right?
When you do that?
And so I can do this red here.
But his brushstrokes
are so much a part of.
My gosh.
I, every time he paints his hair,
he always makes it look absolutely amazing
with this kind of like, sort of mousse
texture and nice and volume and movement.
And I always say
you could achieve it like that.
Or did you know your you your print
like painting technique to your hair?
And that's why I just always look so good.
Okay.
Okay. So.
It's just a little okay.
Okay.
Different.
And then we can go to the.
Okay.
I feel like you should have a bigger,
more gold frame for the other ones, right?
Because I think at the same time,
a frame, especially for Donald Trump is,
not a particularly ornate frame.
But sometimes. I have something.
Which is a name of at my house.
My boss.
But it's into your available tech,
and I don't know, I was first.
Introduced him to my boss's.
Do you not? My new chandelier.
It's just my loves.
Interior decoration. What can we say?
Yeah, there's a lot of those pictures
going on, so I.
Yeah, we do a close up with our hands.
Just.
I don't really look like them.
It's like new Victoria's.
Yeah, exactly.
Yes. It's a very general kind of.
But it's also the chin is more
so more like a movie star.
Yeah. Some subtle surgery.
This with all these models that been
trained on too many photo models.
Yeah.
Pretty.
Scary what you said
about how we might go to the doctor.
The Iron. Man. Is this. Yes.
There we are.
I just read the New Yorker for that.
I got it in the other room.
I never really know if it's like,
the kind of the mythology and,
like the business model.
It's part of saying how scared it is,
I think.
So I think that not happening
is going to kill us all.
Was essentially, we need to be not to do
whatever we want to do, you know, just
and I think some of that was definitely
part of the kind of musk of war, right?
Yeah.
I don't
know, I could be trusted with this,
but, I do think when you talk
to people working and then just like
that.
Yeah, but when I think of it as like,
oh, you like Google actually music.
Because you basically thought
the model was kind of centered.
Yeah, I think it's more and more like
I think it imitates thinking so.
Well, it it's kind of eerie essentially.
Yeah.
You need these moments
where it just acts weird and if you like,
oh, thank God
it's still a computer, right.
Those are the words.
But would be like, really?
The point, like, if you can hide.
Yeah. Stuff.
Yeah, yeah, you can put it.
Oh, sorry.
Okay.
Go for.
Yeah.
Yeah yeah.
Okay.
Thanks. So.
Oh. I,
Yeah.
Okay.
I'm gonna have to go throw.
Out! Gabby.
We all love.
This.
Oh, my.
Life.
Oh, sorry.
The the.
Stuff.
That's the different.
Myself. Oh.
That was like.
Yeah.
Basically, she brought it
back, and that goes into the blueprint.
Yeah.
That works.
That's right. You.
Remember?
Yeah.
Time where I.
Was like.
You talk about.
Haha. Yes.
I brought you here to see Horatio
Nelson, England's great naval hero.
And Nelson's Column is put up immediately
after he wins
the Battle of Trafalgar and is killed
during the Battle of Trafalgar.
And I think it's such a great place to be
to talk about genius, because statues
are one of the ways that we argue about
who deserves to be celebrated.
That's right.
Yeah, we do it.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh yeah.
Because I have no.
Yeah, yeah.
So, Yeah,
we're talking about,
This is a pretty huge pedestal.
And that is Horatio
Nelson, England's great naval hero.
Nelson's column was built
to celebrate his victory over the French
and the Spanish at the Battle
of Trafalgar, at which he also was killed.
And the last couple of years, we've
had all these arguments about statues
and the kind of part of the argument
about genius is to because it's about
who do we celebrate?
And do we still celebrate the same people
that we did 100 years ago, 200 years ago?
So the ratio, Nelson, as far as
I understand, has not been canceled.
But you will walk around London
and see statues of people who at the time
were hailed as geniuses, who we now
feel are a bit more uncomfortable.
There's a very big debate, for example,
about Britain's great war hero
Winston Churchill, but who was also
involved in the Bengal famine.
Actually, one of
the things that's great about being here
is just around the corner behind me.
You can't see it.
There's one of the very few statues
of a named woman, Edith Campbell,
nurse during the First World War.
And actually, one of the things you can
see, we talk about genius being very male.
Statues are very male.
Two, they represent
a very male type of achievement.
And, you know, that's why the
the subject to many of the same debates
that we have over geniuses.
Would say maybe
he got killed.
It definitely helps
because he gave everything for
for his country, you know, and,
and I also think it helps to have
I mean, there's something very funny
almost, about how very big that column is.
It's I think we would say extra.
I don't think they would have described it
that way at me at the time,
but it's very much like
I have got the biggest column.
You know,
there's plenty of statues around London,
but there's only one Nelson's Column.
I know that is about the fact
that he was to the people
who made that the greatest military
hero that we had at the time.
What was it about us.
That we
as a species know
what this is about is that we
like to.
Talk about something like.
I think we love to put people on pedestals
because it's a way of saying what we value
that statue is,
and that column is to commemorate
somebody who gave their life
for an idea of Britain,
an idea of the nation.
Great time.
So many things.
Like.
It's on the mile in the middle of the.
Yeah.
I don't want to get run over that. I mean.
I'm just asking for someone.
Yeah.
What is it about for me personally,
I think we love to hero worship.
I think that's
a pretty natural human impulse.
And also to find out whether or not other
people value the same things that we do.
You know, we don't want to
just listen to record alone.
We want to go to a concert with loads
of other people who like that record, too.
If we hail someone's a genius.
We want to know that other people
value them to the same extent we do.
In the case of a military hero,
you know, that's about saying,
here's an idea of us as a nation
and this is what we all believe.
And, you know, Nelson is a British hero.
But what's interesting about being here is
you can also see the backlash
and follow the square.
So therefore lines
around the base of that plinth,
there's also four separate plinths.
And now for many decades that has been
the idea of the fourth plinth.
And that has been about celebrating
different ideals for a long time.
One of the statues on it,
very famously, was Marc
Quinn's sculpture Alison Lapper Pregnant.
And she had limb
shortening from, for the demise.
And she was pregnant, so she didn't look
like people in classical statues do.
And having that as a public artwork
was about saying we value something
slightly differently.
You know, we don't value
people who are quote unquote perfect.
We value somebody who has made something
about life through struggle.
And they have been more community
based, always about
celebrating minorities
and marginalized people.
And then you can see the push
and pull of the genius myth.
Is it about celebrating
the great man on the pedestal,
or do we need sometimes to celebrate
more ordinary lives, more ordinary people?
Sorry.
And yet
you can't put a team on a pedestal.
That's probably where the genius of teams
is has gone wrong all these years.
Okay, thank you. Yes.
You mentioned the.
I'm not sure all.
I'm going to take you
to see Edith Cavell,
who was a World War One nurse.
And there's something
that's really interesting about the statue
is that she was one of the very,
very few named women to get a statue.
That happens
for all the reasons that you'd expect.
You know, the great historians,
the politicians, the prime ministers
throughout history have been men.
And you get sometimes
these female statues that are
about the personification in victory.
But until very recently,
it has been extremely, extremely
rare to have a woman who is celebrated
enough in her own right to get a statue.
Yes, it's like, well.
That's been around for quite a while,
but we do now have a new one,
which is of Millicent Garrett
Fawcett in Parliament Square.
She was a suffragist.
She campaigned for women to get the vote.
And what is important about that statue
is that it is the first female statue
in Parliament Square, and it's someone
who campaigned for women to get the vote.
So it's about saying women
belong in Parliament, women
belong in Parliament Square.
The genius of someone like Millicent
Garrett Fawcett, who organized
a kind of army of suffragists
that deserves
to be celebrated.
For. It.
So I'm taking you to see Edith Cavell,
who was one of the very
few named women to have a statue in London
or actually anywhere in Britain.
And I always make sure that I come and
look at the statue whenever I walk past.
Phoebe.
That's right.
The night.
So I'm taking you to see Edith Cavell,
who was a nurse
during the First World War.
And she's remarkable
because this is one of the very
few statues we have in London
or anywhere in Britain, of a named woman
who's not Queen Victoria.
There's a few Queen Victoria's.
And I think this is interesting about what
Edith Cowan was being celebrated for.
She was a nurse who treated both Allied
soldiers,
German soldiers,
equally and was executed by firing squad.
And when she died, she said, I bear
no ill will against anyone else.
So she's being celebrated for a kind of
very feminine set of qualities,
which is a bit different
to what Nelson is being celebrated for.
The kind of more male
genius, the military genius.
You know, you know.
That.
Somehow it's also maybe.
I get it like.
We do have these little geniuses,
and now we're sort of starting to order
geniuses. Yeah.
We can say, like.
Who is the,
But she's at all.
It's very tempting to say,
but actually, we can save ourselves
a lot of grief by not putting up statues.
But that's like saying
we shouldn't have geniuses.
The whole point of putting up a statue
is to have an argument about what
you value and what you as a country
and a society value.
And that's exactly the same reason
that we appoint someone to be a genius.
Okay. What do we value in Edith Cavell?
We value sacrifice and duty
and the type of patriotism that she said.
It's not enough to have patriotism.
You also have to kind of
have love for everybody.
That's a specific set of ideals
that are being celebrated here.
And that's the same thing that happens
when we pick a genius.
When we anoint strings, it may sound,
we may know
a Taylor Swift, you know,
what does Taylor Swift represent to us?
Well, talent,
but also hard work, but also,
you know, turning up and putting on a show
every night of the week,
whatever it might be.
It's how we talk about. Our values
and the.
She loves us.
Yeah.
So Edith Havel was a sorry.
So Edith
Cavell was a nurse during the First World
War who treated both sides equally.
But she was executed by a German firing
squad and this was an outrage at the time.
You know, they said, well,
what has she done?
She's not an enemy combatant.
And so there's a statue to her,
which is very rare for a woman,
but because she represents something.
And that's the argument
that I make all the way through.
The genius
myth is that geniuses represent something.
They get statues made to them,
they get museums dedicated to them
because they represent something.
We need to make more
of these people geniuses.
Once we get that.
I think there is a lively debate now about
whether or not she was secretly a spy.
So even the most, you know,
apparently bland celebration of,
you know, sort of nursing duty
might have a little edge to it underneath.
And I don't think you can get away
from those arguments.
You know, what I value is
what I value is always going
to be different to what you value.
And we have to find a way in a society
of kind of finding the middle ground
between those things.
But you might not want that statue.
I might want this one.
You might not want another one.
I might want it.
And that's exactly the same with,
you know, who you hero.
Worship is very different
to who I hero worship.
But yeah, more, more weird statues.
That's what I would like.
One of the things that's been great about
the fourth plinth in Trafalgar Square
is just expanding the range of things
that count as public art,
and I think that's that's wonderful.
Right, right.
Okay, there's one other thing
I can say about this. Be.
For the one.
Of the other things
that's interesting about having public art
of somebody who talked about patriotism
not being enough and died
in the First World War is that you quite
often see anti-war protesters around here,
or people protesting around war crimes.
And statues are a kind of focal point
for those kind of discussions
in exactly the same way that it mattered.
But Albert Einstein was very worried
about the nuclear bomb,
because there was a person
that you could point to, a focus,
a rallying point around
which you could have this big argument.
He's a genius. He's worried about this.
That makes it okay
for us to worry about it, too.
Edith Cavell
shows in the dark side of of War,
not the kind of glory
and the patriotism of it.
So she becomes a focal point for people
to talk about things that they want
to talk about.
Let's stop here.
Okay.
It's on my way to work.
So I kind of say hello to her quite often
in the morning when I go past, I don't
I don't say hello to Nelson.
I don't know that much about Nelson.
And that's one of the interesting things
too, is that Nelson is a figure
of national mythology
for British people, for English people,
but actually not in the culture
in a particularly strong way.
It will take somebody deciding
that they love Nelson,
they want to make the Nelson biopic
or whatever it is to bring him back again.
But yeah, I do, I do.
Stop and say hello to Edith.
Travel in the morning. But.
He has a bit of a tormented forward.
Kind of coping.
I think that's just the extremely high
neckline.
Yeah,
but it's interesting that she's
she's posed in a very heroic way.
It's a very kind of it's
a very, like, manly striding pose.
And again, that's why statues are part
of the kind of iconography of genius
it's about in the same way
the portraits are, it's about presenting
somebody as being grandeur.
Why statues big?
Why are people so often on horseback?
It's about saying that they are
superhuman.
They're different to us somehow.
They're not like ordinary people.
The geniuses.
Thanks
for the rain.
Yeah.
That.
Is is it
the offices in.
Thank local radio.
The barn.
The kind of,
more popular of the people.
But sometimes you have cities. We have.
Parts where it's just like, oh, that's.
Great,
right?
Yeah.
That's.
Just.
Yeah.
Going.
Going to start to.
Send that to them.
And the other one for.
Okay.
That's fine for.
Yourself.
Okay. You're going
you're they, you're.
I it.
Looks like a whole.
The, like the ground floor.
Your heart.
Will be the
on the kind of the home again.
And there will be.
More resources.
There.
When you're ready for.
Really?
Next, next.
Month from there,
we will follow you all the way around. We.
Will ask you a question there.
Or maybe here for a.
Yeah, yeah.
So this is.
About this as great man as it gets, right?
Was Winston Churchill a genius?
If you want to start a fight
in a pub in Britain,
that's a pretty good question
to throw out there.
To some people, Winston
Churchill is unquestionably a genius.
If you look at how he came to power,
the Nazis were on the march.
Britain was pursuing
a policy of appeasement,
and he was the person who came in
and said, there's you know, Britain
fights on Britain and Britain alone
will stand against the Nazis,
and therefore he's a national hero.
But there are some checkered bits
in the back story, too.
He will too.
Lots of people forever be associated
with the Bengal famine, which left
millions dead in his career
as a kind of colonial overseer.
And so people have these big debates,
which is the real Winston Churchill.
Is he the genius who galvanized
this nation to stand against Nazis,
or is he the kind of feckless
colonialist of the Bengal famine?
Maybe he's and he's both.
I mean,
this is why we can always argue
about geniuses, because he's both
you know, I think there's a huge amount
to be proud of.
Winston Churchill.
But we don't need to airbrush
out the bad bits of the biography two.
In fact, they're more interesting because
they're what makes him human, right?
He's not just the guy on the pedestal.
He was a real human being.
And, you know, the other thing
that's become part of his mythology
in recent years
is the black dog, his depression.
He was somebody who suffered from really
poor mental health at certain times.
But there's something noble
about the way that he nonetheless
galvanized himself and the country
that really difficult and dark moments.
Because also say something about us
that we need
people like this
to have these kind of the trenches of
torment
where we used to just be like,
oh, he's a war hero, great guy.
I think that's the thing
I think people were more comfortable
at just having a straightforward
mythology of the great man.
Now we want to hear about
how did the great man struggle
and what did the great man
find difficult to do?
And we want to see the real person
underneath.
You know, if you watch
I watched The Darkest Hour,
which is a Churchill biopic,
and there's scenes of him in the bath
and this would have been,
you know, in 1950,
that would have been a really shocking
thing to, to say and talk about.
And now we kind of want that.
We want the human side of the genius.
Would you
say he's like
an example of the queen of this great man
theory of history, but also a great man?
I think he's an obvious example
of a great man of history.
That decision to replace
Neville Chamberlain with Winston Churchill
is a pivotal moment
in the Second World War,
and that is exactly what Great man
theory is all about.
It's about one person being
vitally important to the course of events.
It's a part of who you stand on.
Why do I stand on Winston Churchill?
Yes. Oh, no.
Look, I think that maybe.
The Winston Churchill genius.
Or Winston Churchill,
a political genius, undoubtedly,
because what he did was taking a country
that needed to believe in itself
to do something
which was undoubtedly morally correct,
which was stand against the Nazis.
And he did that.
He pulled everybody together.
And to me, that is still
one of the most extraordinary
things in Britain's history, and something
I think that Britain can still,
80 years on, be incredibly proud about.
But but I to say that I don't need
to airbrush out
the earlier Winston Churchill
and I think that's the thing.
But what do you think about people
like that?
You should have your you.
You shouldn't, like, pry
too much into these lines or.
There it's a left wing, right
wing argument essentially,
which is there's a feeling
that if you debunk Winston Churchill,
that's taking something away from Britain,
that's taking away a particular story
of Britain's history, saying
maybe Britain should be a bit more ashamed
of its past versus people who say Britain,
we should be proud of our history.
And this is an argument
that happens across Europe,
it happens in America,
it happens in Britain.
And genius is a part of that story.
Can you be proud of a genius?
Can you be proud of an English genius
and what they say about England?
And that's wrapped up in
questions about patriotism.
I guess is right.
It is really the change.
Yeah. That's right.
Today I get this,
you have this right
with the French, right?
Just about all the stuff during the game.
Powers like this guy.
Right?
With regret,
for instance,
that you should feel about this, right?
Community. Yeah.
And we're all ready for the fight.
He basically feels like this,
Let's face it this way.
Some get the feeling.
You know, I think you.
I think you have to be an adult
about this stuff.
I think that the fact that
Winston Churchill.
Even more,
I think after you said
with these rifles and.
I'm going zero, but.
Okay,
let's go through what can we just do?